<Skills>
    <Skill>
        <Name>Attack</Name>
        <Stat>Str</Stat>
        <Cost>5</Cost>
        <Synergy>Warrior</Synergy>
        <Text>
            With a powerful swipe of their claws the lycan attacks their victim.
            The skill <name>Attack</name> is an attack of power <check type="str">Attack+1</check>. The damage it deals is equal to its power. Multiple attackers can use <name>Attack</name> to grapple a defender. See Grappled for details.
            The character must either be in Warg Form, Wolf Form or carrying a weapon to use <name>Attack</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Attack</Action>
            <Power type="roll" add="1" weapon="1"><skill>Attack</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Attack for X damage.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Backstab</Name>
        <Require>Attack</Require>
        <Stat>Dex</Stat>
        <Cost>2</Cost>
        <Synergy>Rogue</Synergy>
        <Text>
            Unseen and unheard the skilled rogue can approach a victim and take the time necessary to ensure that the blow they strike is precise and effective.
            A character who is hidden or moving silently can perform a <name>Backstab</name> of power <check type="dex">Attack+Backstab</check>. The attacker may use the +3 bonus for attacking an unaware defender. The damage of this attack is equal to its power.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Attack</Action>
            <Mana>5</Mana>
            <Power type="roll" weapon="1"><skill>Attack</skill><skill>Backstab</skill></Power>
            <Quick> If unseen, attack for X damage.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Berserk</Name>
        <Require>Attack</Require>
        <Stat>Str</Stat>
        <Cost>2</Cost>
        <Synergy>Warrior</Synergy>
        <Text>
            Whipping themselves into a fury the character loses track of everything but inflicting pain on those around them.
            The power of this skill is <check type="str">Berserk</check>. The duration of this skill is equal to its power and cannot be stopped before this. Each turn the character must make an attack with power and damage equal to <check type="str">Berserk<times/>2</check>. They may choose the target but must pick a conscious target if one exists. If there are no conscious targets they must target unconscious living targets. If there are no living targets they must target dead creatures.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Attack</Action>
            <Power type="roll" times="2" weapon="1"><skill>Berserk</skill></Power>
            <Duration type="roll"><skill>Berserk</skill></Duration>
            <Quick>Must attack for Y turns. Each turn roll an attack for X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Black Hole</Name>
        <Require>Portal</Require>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Spell>Oxdoro</Spell>
        <Cost>5</Cost>
        <Synergy>Mechanist</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Oxdoro</name> the character is able to bend space in on itself creating a point in space that sucks everything towards it and crushes those inside.
            The power of this skill is <check type="fai">Black Hole</check>. The duration of <name>Black Hole</name> is equal to its power in turns. Anyone within a radius in metres equal to the power of this skill is immediately sent to the centre of the hole even if other objects or characters are already there. Anyone starting their turn in the hole takes damage equal to the power of this skill and cannot move out of the centre of the hole.
            This skill requires a <name>Major Action</name> to cast and each following turn to sustain it. The character does not <name>Refresh</name> their <MP/> for the duration of this skill. Note that if the caster is within the radius of the hole then they too are sucked into the centre.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>M</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Black Hole</skill></Power>
            <Duration>X</Duration>
            <Quick>Create a black hole radius X that sucks objects in.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Bless</Name>
        <Name>Curse</Name>
        <Invert/>
        <Divide/>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Spell>Loreanna</Spell>
        <Cost>3</Cost>
        <Synergy>Trickster</Synergy>
        <Text>
            Calling on the power of <name>Loreanna</name> fortune favours someone in all they do.
            The power of the skill is <check type="fai">Bless</check>. The target character gains +2 to all skill checks or -2 to all skill checks in any skill that they have spent <XP/> on. The duration of the effect is equal to its power. This effect is <name>Dividable</name> so by reducing the duration the user can give a larger bonus or penalty to skill checks. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>4</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Bless</skill></Power>
            <Duration>X</Duration>
            <Quick>Target gets +2 or -2 to all skills.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Blink</Name>
        <Require>Dodge</Require>
        <Stat>Dex</Stat>
        <Spell>Oxdoro</Spell>
        <Cost>3</Cost>
        <Synergy>Mechanist</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Oxdoro</name> the character can quickly bend space so as to travel a short distance without moving.
            If used as a defence the power of this skill is <check type="dex">Dodge+Blink</check>. If the power of the attack is equal to or less than this power then the attack deals no damage nor has any effect on the defender.
            If used as a method of travel the power of this skill is <check type="dex">Blink</check>. In this case the user may move a distance in metres equal to the power of the skill to any visible location. Casting requires a <name>Minor Action</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Defend</Action>
            <Mana>1</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Blink</skill><skill>Dodge</skill></Power>
            <Quick>If X at least attack, then no damage or effect.</Quick>
        </Effect>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Minor</Action>
            <Mana>1</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Blink</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Move a distance of up to X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Block</Name>
        <Require>Attack</Require>
        <Stat>Str</Stat>
        <Cost>4</Cost>
        <Synergy>Warrior</Synergy>
        <Text>
            With a quick response and powerful intent the defender can reduce the impact of any blow.
            Attacks can be defended with a power of <check type="str">Block</check>. Any attack has its power reduced by the power of this skill. If the attack power is reduced to 0 then it also has no effect. If an attack targets multiple characters the attack power is only reduced to this defending character.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Defend</Action>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Block</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Reduce the power of an attack by X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Bloodlust</Name>
        <Require>Attack</Require>
        <Stat>Str</Stat>
        <Cost>2</Cost>
        <Synergy>Warrior</Synergy>
        <Text>
            Sadistically revelling in the misfortune of their target the character gains power as they attack their opponent.
            The power of the attack is <check type="str">Bloodlust</check>. This attack deals damage equal to the power of the attack and gains <HP>1</HP> for each 2 damage done.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Attack</Action>
            <Mana>2</Mana>
            <Power type="roll" weapon="1"><skill>Bloodlust</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Attack for X. Gain 1 HP for each 2 damage done.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Chain Lightning</Name>
        <Require>Lightning Bolt</Require>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>1</Cost>
        <Spell>Arthur</Spell>
        <Synergy>Battle Mage</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Arthur</name> the caster is able to channel energy to form a massive bolt of lightning that bounces between foes.
            The power of the attack is <check type="fai">Chain Lightning</check>. The caster determines the initial trajectory and can change this trajectory a number of times equal to <half/> of the power of this skill. Each time the bolt travels in a straight line and hits all characters it crosses. The total distance that the bolt travels is equal to the power of the skill in metres however will stop prior to this if it hits a wall or similarly grounded object.
            The bolt deals damage equal to its power to every creature it passes. Creatures can be hit by the same bolt more than once however they are only targeted by the attack once and so only need to defend once.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Attack</Action>
            <Mana>4</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Chain Lightning</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Attack for X. May re-target X/2 times</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Charm</Name>
        <Name>Confuse</Name>
        <Require>Fear</Require>
        <Invert/>
        <Stat>Int</Stat>
        <Cost>4</Cost>
        <Spell>Ird'ken</Spell>
        <Synergy>Channeller</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Ird'ken</name> the caster can bend the will of their target to their own or simply shatter it.
            When used to charm the power of this skill is <check type="fai">Charm<times/>2</check>. If the power of this skill is greater than the <MP/> of the target then the target is charmed. This means that the target will obey the caster as long as the caster does not require them to go against the principles or motivations of the target. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
            When used to confuse the power of this skill is <check type="fai">Confuse<times/>2</check>. If the power of this skill is greater than the <MP/> of the target then the target becomes confused and aggressive. While in this state the target will not see the difference between friend and foe, attacking the nearest target. If the attack is on a friend then the caster chooses which skill will be used. If the attack is on a foe then the target chooses which skill will be used. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>5,2</Mana>
            <Power type="roll" times="2"><skill>Charm</skill></Power>
            <Quick>If X is at least target's MP they are charmed.</Quick>
        </Effect>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>5,2</Mana>
            <Power type="roll" times="2"><skill>Confuse</skill></Power>
            <Quick>If X is at least target's MP they become confused, attacking characters randomly.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Cleave</Name>
        <Require>Attack</Require>
        <Stat>Str</Stat>
        <Cost>2</Cost>
        <Synergy>Warrior</Synergy>
        <Text>
            With broad powerful strokes the attacker can engage multiple foes at once.
            The power of the attack is <check type="str">Cleave</check>. The skill deals damage equal to its power to all adjacent characters, friend and foe alike.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Attack</Action>
            <Mana>1</Mana>
            <Power type="roll" weapon="1"><skill>Cleave</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Attack all adjacent characters for X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Combo</Name>
        <Require>Attack</Require>
        <Stat>Dex</Stat>
        <Cost>2</Cost>
        <Synergy>Rogue</Synergy>
        <Text>
            While appearing slow at first the attacker gains momentum and blow follows blow at last wreaking massive damage to any foolhardy enough to get in the attacker's way.
            If the attacker's last action was not a successful attack or they choose to restart the <name>Combo</name> the skill's power is <check type="dex">Combo</check>. The attack costs <MP>0</MP> and deals damage equal to its power.
            If the attacker's last action was a successful attack then the skill's power is <check type="dex">Combo</check> plus the result of the previous attack after defense. The attack costs <MP>2</MP> plus the cost of the last attack. The attack deals damage equal to its power.
            This means that the power and mana cost of the attack accumulates with successful attacks.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Attack</Action>
            <Mana>0</Mana>
            <Power type="roll" weapon="1"><skill>Combo</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Attack for X costing 0 MP.</Quick>
        </Effect>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Attack</Action>
            <Mana>X+2</Mana>
            <Power type="roll" weapon="1"><skill>Combo</skill></Power>
            <Quick>If last Major Action was a successful attack then attack for X+last result and costing 2+last MP.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Control Undead</Name>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>5</Cost>
        <Spell>Innodi</Spell>
        <Synergy>Necromancer</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Innodi</name> a character can bend the minds of creatures with abnormal life to their will.
            The power of the skill is <check type="fai">Control Undead</check>. This power can be split in any way among any number of undead creatures to change whose control they are under. The power required to control a creature not currently controlled is equal to the creature's power. If the creature is currently under control then  twice the creature's power is required. If the creature is currently under control and only the creature's power is reached then the creature is no longer under anyones control. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
            Any controlled undead can be dismissed for <MP>3</MP>. The character gains <HP>1</HP> for each undead dismissed in this way. Dismissing requires a <name>Minor Action</name> however any number of undead can be dismissed at once for <MP>3</MP>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>2</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Control Undead</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Gain control of an undead/golem not under anyones control of level less than X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>2</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Control Undead</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Target undead/golem of level less than X is no longer under anyones control.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Counter</Name>
        <Require>Deflect</Require>
        <Stat>Dex</Stat>
        <Cost>2</Cost>
        <Synergy>Rogue</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By using the attackers own strength against them the defender quickly turns the blow destined for them to the back to attacker themselves.
            The power of the skill is <check type="dex">Counter+1</check>. If this power is equal to or greater than the power of the attack then the attack deals no damage nor has any effect. In this case the attacker receives damage equal to the power of this skilll and any effects that the defender would have received. This damage is not considered an attack and so cannot be defended against.
            This skill cannot be used to defend against projectile attacks.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Defend</Action>
            <Mana>1</Mana>
            <Power type="roll" add="1"><skill>Counter</skill></Power>
            <Quick>If X is at least attack then take no damage and attacker takes X damage.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Counter-spell</Name>
        <Stat>Int</Stat>
        <Cost>2</Cost>
        <Synergy>Channeller</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By interjecting in the target's commune with their deity the character skilfully disrupts the flow of power towards themselves rendering the divine power completely ineffective.
            The power of this skill is <check type="int">Counter-spell</check>. If this power is equal to or greater than the power of a spell just cast targeting the user then all effects of that spell do not occur. A countered spell still requires it's casting cost although no ongoing costs are required. Using this skill requires a <name>Minor Action</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Minor</Action>
            <Mana>5</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Counter-spell</skill></Power>
            <Quick>If X is at least spell power targeting the character then it is cancelled.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Create Golem</Name>
        <Name>Destroy Golem</Name>
        <Require>Raise Undead</Require>
        <Invert/>
        <Divide/>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>2</Cost>
        <Spell>Innodi</Spell>
        <Synergy>Necromancer</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Innodi</name> a character can bring earth and fire to life to fight at their side.
            When creating a golem the power of this skill is <check type="fai">Create Golem</check>. The user can create a <name>Golem</name> of level up to the power of this skill. This effect is <name>Dividable</name> and so level of creature can be sacrificed for quantity of creatures. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name> and sufficent earth or fire source dependant on the type of <name>Golem</name>. The casting creates the form so the earth or fire do not have to be shaped by hand.
            For example a character with a check of 9 can create one <name>Golem</name> with level up to 9. They could also create two <name>Golem</name>s with level up to 4 or 3 <name>Golem</name>s with level up to 2.
            This skill costs <MP>1</MP> to sustain for each <name>Golem</name>.
            When destroying a golem the power of this skill is <check type="fai">Destroy Golem</check>. The golem loses power equal to the power of this skill. If the golem falls below <HP>0</HP> or reaches power 0 then it is destroyed.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>5,X</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Create Golem</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Create a golem of power X. Divide power to add a golem. Cost to sustain is equal to number of golems.</Quick>
        </Effect>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Minor</Action>
            <Mana>5</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Destroy Golem</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Remove X power from a summoned Golem.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Devour</Name>
        <Require>Bloodlust</Require>
        <Stat>Str</Stat>
        <Cost>1</Cost>
        <Synergy>Warrior</Synergy>
        <Text>
            Taking advantage of the power of a fallen foe the character consumes their body to restore their own power.
            When used on an incapacitated target the target causes <check type="str">Devour</check> <name>Deep Wounds</name>. For each <name>Deep Wound</name> the target sustains the character gains <HP>1</HP>. Devouring requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Attack</Action>
            <Mana>2</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Devour</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Gain X HP and deal X deep wound to incapacitated foe.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Deflect</Name>
        <Require>Dodge</Require>
        <Stat>Dex</Stat>
        <Cost>2</Cost>
        <Synergy>Rogue</Synergy>
        <Text>
            Spotting weakness in a character's attack the defender swiftly parries and opens the attacker for a quick riposte.
            The power of the defence is <check type="dex">Deflect+1</check>. If this power is equal to or greater than the power of the attack then it deals no damage nor has any effect and the attacker is <name>Stun</name>ned for 1 turn. Note that <name>Tough Fighter</name> does not affect this skill.
            This skill cannot be used to defend against projectile attacks.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Defend</Action>
            <Mana>1</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Deflect</skill></Power>
            <Quick>If X is at least attack power then take no damage and attacker is stunned for 1 turn.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Divine Arrow</Name>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>5</Cost>
        <Spell>Arthur</Spell>
        <Synergy>Battle Mage</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of Arthur the caster summons an arrow from the ether and fires it at its hapless victim.
            The power of the attack is <check type="fai">Divine Arrow</check>. It deals damage equal to it's power.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Attack</Action>
            <Mana>2</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Divine Arrow</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Attack for X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Divine Contract</Name>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>1</Cost>
        <Spell>Ird'ken</Spell>
        <Synergy>Channeller</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Ird'ken</name> the caster binds their will into the fate of their target.
            The power of this skill is equal to its level. A willing target must complete a goal specified by the caster. If they fail this goal they immediately receive <check type="fai">power<times/>5</check> <name>Deep Wound</name>s to a maximum of the target's <HPMax/>.
            While this skill is a spell it is unaffected by <name>Counter-spell</name>, <name>Spell Shield</name>, <name>Inversion</name> and <name>Steal Spell</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>M</Mana>
            <Power type="roll" times="5"><skill>Divine Contract</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Willing target must obey contract. If they fail to roll for X and they take X deep wounds.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Dodge</Name>
        <Stat>Dex</Stat>
        <Cost>3</Cost>
        <Synergy>Rogue</Synergy>
        <Text>
            With a swift and quick step the defender avoids even the most massive attack.
            The power of this skill is <check type="dex">Dodge+1</check>. If this power is equal to or greater than the attack power the it deals no damage nor has any effect on the defender.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Defend</Action>
            <Power type="roll" add="1"><skill>Dodge</skill></Power>
            <Quick>If X is at least attack power then take no damage.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Endurance</Name>
        <Stat>Str</Stat>
        <Cost>1</Cost>
        <Text>
            This character is strong and has learnt to endure even the harshest conditions.
            The character can attempt a dead lift of any object with power equal to <check type="str">Endurance</check>. If the value of power<times/>20kg is greater than the weight of the object then it can be lifted.
            Unskilled <Str/> actions can be performed with a power of <check type="str">Endurance+1</check>. Any skill with an <Str/> icon requires this skill.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Endurance</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Lift objects up to X times 20kg.</Quick>
        </Effect>
        <Effect>
            <Power type="roll" add="1"><skill>Endurance</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Unskilled Str action with power X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Extra HP</Name>
        <Cost>5</Cost>
        <Synergy>Warrior</Synergy>
        <Text>
            The character is healthy beyond normal bounds.
            Each level of this skill increases the character's maximum <HP/> by three. As death occurs at -<HPMax/> this skill increases the range that a character will remain unconscious but not dead.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Power times="3"><skill>Extra HP</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Character gains +X to max HP.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Extra MP</Name>
        <Cost>5</Cost>
        <Synergy>Trickster</Synergy>
        <Text>
            This character has willpower beyond normal bounds. Each level of this skill increases the character's maximum <MP/> by three.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Power times="3"><skill>Extra MP</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Character gains +X to max MP</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Fear</Name>
        <Name>Anger</Name>
        <Invert/>
        <Stat>Int</Stat>
        <Cost>4</Cost>
        <Spell>Ird'ken</Spell>
        <Synergy>Channeller</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Ird'ken</name> the caster can instill fear into a single target or make a character unquestionably the target of attack.
            When used to cause fear this skill has power <check type="fai">Fear<times/>2</check>. If the power of the skill is greater than the <MP/> of the target then the target becomes afraid of the caster and may not attack them under any circumstances and will try to avoid them as much a possible. If the power of the skill is greater than twice the <MP/> of the target then the target will attempt to flee. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
            When used to anger this skill has power <check type="fai">Anger<times/>2</check>. To use this skill a single character is chosen and the skill targets all characters who are opposed to the chosen character. All targeted characters with <MP/> less than the power of this skill must attack the chosen character. The attackers may use any attack skill they wish and if it is impossible for them to attack the target they may take whatever action they wish. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>3,1</Mana>
            <Power type="roll" times="2"><skill>Fear</skill></Power>
            <Quick>If X is at least targets MP then target fears the caster.</Quick>
        </Effect>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>3,1</Mana>
            <Power type="roll" times="2"><skill>Fear</skill></Power>
            <Quick>If X is at least targets MP then target attacks a scapegoat.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Fireball</Name>
        <Require>Divine Arrow</Require>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>2</Cost>
        <Spell>Arthur</Spell>
        <Synergy>Battle Mage</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Arthur</name> the caster is able to channel energy to form a ball of fire which is then hurled at its hapless victims exploding on contact.
            The power of this skill is <check type="fai">Fireball</check>. This skill deals damage equal to its power and has radius equal to <half/> of its power in metres. A character that receives at least 5 damage from this skill is <name>On Fire</name> with power equal to the power of this skill.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Attack</Action>
            <Mana>4</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Fireball</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Attack anyone in radius of X/2 for X. If X is at least 5 then on fire for X as well.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Focus</Name>
        <Cost>3</Cost>
        <Synergy>Rogue</Synergy>
        <Text>
            While the physical limits of the character have not changed through force of willpower a character maintains consciousness while badly injured.
            For each level in this skill the range in which a character remains conscious is increased by 3. A character will die by falling below -<HPMax/> regardless of this skill. Regain consciousness rolls are unaffected by this skill. A character with this skill still needs to return to positive health and make a regular regain conscoiusness roll once unconscious.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Power times="3"><skill>Focus</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Stay conscious until -X HP</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Fog</Name>
        <Name>Wind</Name>
        <Invert/>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>2</Cost>
        <Spell>Innodi</Spell>
        <Synergy>Necromancer</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Innodi</name> the caster can summon a great fog concealing all or a great wind.
            If attempting to create a fog the power of the skill is <check type="fai">Fog</check>. The radius of the fog is the skills power in metres. Any character attempting to move more than one meter in a turn must make a <check type="dex">Sprint</check> roll greater than the power of the fog or fall over. Ranged non-area effect attacks cannot be made and mêlée attacks are reduced by the power of the fog. Every character in the fog gains the power of the skill in <name>Stealth</name>. The fog takes one turn to dissipate. It costs no mana for this turn but has full effect during that turn.
            If attempting to create a great wind the power of the skill is <check type="fai">Fog</check>. The radius of the wind is equal to its power. Any character in the blast must make a <check type="dex">Sprint</check> check and if this roll is less than the power of the wind they will fall over after travelling a distance in metres equal to the check. Any type of fog in the area of the blast will have its power reduced by the power of the wind to a minimum of zero at which the fog has completely dissipated.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>3,1</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Fog</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Create a fog of strength X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>3,1</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Wind</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Create a wind of strength X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Haste</Name>
        <Name>Slow</Name>
        <Invert/>
        <Divide/>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>5</Cost>
        <Spell>Oxdoro</Spell>
        <Synergy>Mechanist</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Oxdoro</name> the caster can create a pocket of space containing a single character where the flow of time is altered.
            The power of this skill is <check type="fai">Haste</check>. The target gains +1 or -1 to <name>Speed</name> for a duration equal to this skill's power in turns. This effect is <name>Dividable</name> and so duration can be halved to add an additional +1 or -1 to speed. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>10</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Haste</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Target character gains +1 or -1 to their speed. Divide to add an additional +1 or -1.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Heal</Name>
        <Name>Hurt</Name>
        <Invert/>
        <Divide/>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>5</Cost>
        <Spell>Innodi</Spell>
        <Synergy>Necromancer</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Innodi</name> the caster can directly heal the life force or drain the life force from a creature.
            The power of the skill is <check type="fai">Heal</check>. This skill can increase or reduce the <HP/> of a character by the power of the skill in <HP/>. This skill is not an attack skill and hence when it is used to reduce a characters <HP/> the target cannot use a defence skill. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>. Note that this skill can raise a character's <HP/> above <HPMax/>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>4</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Heal</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Target gains or loses X HP.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Heal Deep Wounds</Name>
        <Name>Cause Deep Wounds</Name>
        <Require>Heal</Require>
        <Invert/>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>5</Cost>
        <Spell>Innodi</Spell>
        <Synergy>Necromancer</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Innodi</name> the caster can heal even the most dire of wounds, or cause them.
            The power of this skill is <check type="fai">Heal Deep Wounds</check>. This skill can reduce the number of <name>Deep Wounds</name> by its power or alternatively can cause cause a number of <name>Deep Wounds</name> equal to its power. If used to heal <name>Deep Wounds</name> and the power of this skill is greater than the number <name>Deep Wounds</name> then the remaining power is used to heal regular wounds. The casting time is around one minute.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>M</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Heal Deep Wounds</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Target gains or loses X deep wounds</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Hold Person</Name>
        <Name>Free Person</Name>
        <Invert/>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>5</Cost>
        <Spell>Oxdoro</Spell>
        <Synergy>Mechanist</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Oxdoro</name> the caster can magically bind creature in one spot.
            The power of this skill is <check type="fai">Hold Person</check>. The maximum duration of the skill is equal to its power. The target can no longer move and so on their turn cannot move, take a <name>Major Action</name> nor any action that requires movement. They still get a <name>Minor Action</name> however they may not use it to perform any physical action apart from speaking or casting spells. This skill requires a <name>Major Action</name> to cast and then a <name>Major Action</name> each following turn to sustain it.
            Alternatively any target character now has a normal movement phase and <name>Major Action</name> whether or not another skill restricts them. This does not provide any effect on an unconscious character however does grant a <name>Major Action</name> to someone under the effects of a <name>Slow</name> spell. This skill requires a <name>Major Action</name> to sustain it.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>4,2</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Hold Person</skill></Power>
            <Duration>X</Duration>
            <Quick>Target has no Major Action, or if they have no Major Action they now have one.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Inferno</Name>
        <Require>Fireball</Require>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>1</Cost>
        <Spell>Arthur</Spell>
        <Synergy>Battle Mage</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Arthur</name> the character creates an explosion of flame emanating from the character in all directions.
            The power of this skill is <check type="fai">Inferno</check>. The radius of this effect is equal to the power of this skill in metres, excluding the caster, and the damage is equal to its power. Anyone who takes damage from this skill is <name>On Fire</name> with power equal to the power of this skill. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Attack</Action>
            <Mana>5</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Inferno</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Attack everyone in a radius of X for X and they are on fire for X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Impenetrable Field</Name>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>3</Cost>
        <Spell>Arthur</Spell>
        <Synergy>Battle Mage</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Arthur</name> the caster creates a barrier that protects them from any harm.
            The power of this skill is <check type="fai">Impenetrable Field</check>. The field has <HP/> equal to the power of the skill. The field has the skill <name>Block</name> at the level of half the power of this skill. When any attacker targets the character they target the field instead. When the field drops to <HP>0</HP> it is destroyed and any remaining damage targets the character instead. During the Refresh and Regenerate phase of Combat the field loses <HP>1</HP>. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>5</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Impenetrable Field</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Gain a field with HP of X and Block at level X/2</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Increase Size</Name>
        <Name>Reduce Size</Name>
        <Invert/>
        <Divide/>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>4</Cost>
        <Spell>Oxdoro</Spell>
        <Synergy>Mechanist</Synergy>
        <Text>
            Calling on the power of <name>Oxdoro</name> the character can warp the size of any creature or object.
            The power of the skill is <check type="fai">Alter Size</check>. The target either gains a size class or loses a size class, decided by the user. The duration of the skill is equal to the power of the skill. This effect is <name>Dividable</name> so by sacrificing duration the character can add or subtract an additional size class. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
            For rules on size classes and effects see <name>Altered Size</name> for details.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>5</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Increase Size</skill></Power>
            <Duration>X</Duration>
            <Quick>Target gains or loses a size class. Divide to add or lose an additional class.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Increase Stat</Name>
        <Name>Reduce Stat</Name>
        <Divide/>
        <Invert/>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>5</Cost>
        <Spell>Loreanna</Spell>
        <Synergy>Trickster</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Loreanna</name> a character suddenly becomes more powerful in a specific way.
            The power of this skill is <check type="fai">Change Stat</check>. The caster chooses either <Str/>, <Dex/>, <Int/> or <Fai/> and the target gains an extra die level or loses a die level to that stat for a duration equal to the power of the skill. This effect is <name>Dividable</name> so by reducing the duration the caster can increase the number of dice levels gained or lost. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>5</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Increase Stat</skill></Power>
            <Duration>X</Duration>
            <Quick>Target gains +1 or -1 to either Str, Dex, Int or Fai. Divide for an additional +1 or -1.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Increase Stats</Name>
        <Name>Reduce Stats</Name>
        <Require>Increase Stat</Require>
        <Invert/>
        <Divide/>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>3</Cost>
        <Spell>Loreanna</Spell>
        <Synergy>Trickster</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of Loreanna a character suddenly becomes more powerful in every way.
            The power of this skill is <check type="fai">Change Stats</check>. The target gains an extra die level or loses a die level to all of <Str/>, <Dex/>, <Int/> and <Fai/> for a duration qual to the power of the skill. This effect is <name>Dividable</name> so by reducing the duration the caster can increase the number of dice levels gained or lost. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>7</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Increase Stats</skill></Power>
            <Duration>X</Duration>
            <Quick>Target gains +1 or -1 to all of Str, Dex, Int and Fai. Divide for an additional +1 or -1.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Initiative</Name>
        <Stat>Int</Stat>
        <Cost>2</Cost>
        <Synergy>Rogue</Synergy>
        <Text>
            Ever ready for action the character anticipates the actions of others.
            This skill is used at the start of combat. The power is <check type="int">Initiative+1</check>. The turn order of characters is determined by the highest power of this skill. If there is a tie then then the characters that tied reroll to see who goes first amongst themselves.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Power type="roll" add="1"><skill>Initiative</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Roll for X at start of combat. Turn order is descending X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Inversion</Name>
        <Require>Counter-spell</Require>
        <Stat>Int</Stat>
        <Cost>3</Cost>
        <Synergy>Channeller</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By carefully disrupting the communication between a caster and their deity they can, in some way, reverse the effect of a spell.
            The power of this skill is <check type="int">Inversion</check>. If the power of this skill is equal to or greater than the power of a spell just cast targeting the user then the spell targets the caster instead or a spell that is invertible uses the inverse ability but not both. The caster still pays the casting cost but the character may, if they choose to, pay the ongoing costs to increase its duration in the same way that the original caster could. Casting requires a <name>Minor Action</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Minor</Action>
            <Mana>6</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Inversion</skill></Power>
            <Quick>If X is at least the power of a spell then either its effect is inverted or it targets the caster instead.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Invisibility</Name>
        <Name>Locate</Name>
        <Require>Light</Require>
        <Invert/>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>1</Cost>
        <Spell>Loreanna</Spell>
        <Synergy>Trickster</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Loreanna</name> the caster can either detect the presence of an object or conceal it from view.
            If trying to conceal a character or object the power is <check type="fai">Invisibility</check>. If it is an object it reduces the power of any <name>Observation</name> check targeting the object by the power of this skill. Note that this skill does not affect <name>Sense</name> checks. If a character is targeted they gain the power of this skill to their <name>Stealth</name> skill regardless of whether they have spent points in that skill or not. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
            If trying to find a character or object the power of this skill is <check type="fai">Locate</check>. The surrounds of an object are known at a radius equal to the power of this skill in metres. If the character is within this radius they know the exact location of the object otherwise they only know the direction of the object. Casting requires a <name>Minor Action</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Minor</Action>
            <Mana>2,1</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Invisibility</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Target gains +X to the result of any stealth rolls</Quick>
        </Effect>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Minor</Action>
            <Mana>2</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Locate</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Find an object within a radius of X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Light</Name>
        <Name>Darkness</Name>
        <Invert/>
        <Divide/>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>3</Cost>
        <Spell>Loreanna</Spell>
        <Synergy>Trickster</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Loreanna</name> the caster can channel light either shinning with divine light or sucking the light out of the environment.
            This skill can, without a check or <MP/> cost, produce sufficient light to see by under any non-divine conditions. Casting requires a <name>Minor Action</name>.
            The power of this skill <check type="fai">Light</check>. The caster can increase or reduce the light in the current location by one for a duration equal to the power of this skill. See <name>Environmental Light</name> for details. This effect is <name>Dividable</name> so by reducing the duration the caster can increase or decrease the light further. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Minor</Action>
            <Mana>2</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Light</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Increase or reduce light level by one. Divide to add or reduce by a further one.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Lightning Bolt</Name>
        <Require>Divine Arrow</Require>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>3</Cost>
        <Spell>Arthur</Spell>
        <Synergy>Battle Mage</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Arthur</name> the caster is able to channel energy to form a massive bolt of lightning to strike their foes.
            The power of the skill is <check type="fai">Lightning Bolt</check>. The path of the bolt is a line starting at the character and will continue for the power of the skill in metres or until it hits a wall or similarly grounded object. Every character in this path takes damage equal to the power of this skill.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Attack</Action>
            <Mana>5</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Lightning Bolt</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Attack for X everyone in a line of length X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Locks and Traps</Name>
        <Stat>Dex</Stat>
        <Cost>3</Cost>
        <Synergy>Rogue</Synergy>
        <Text>
            The character is especially skilled at mechanisms. This provides them the ability to manipulate mechanical locks and traps as well as the experience necessary to observe the location of traps.
            If the character is attempting to pick a mechanical lock the power of this skill is <check type="dex">Locks and Traps</check>. If the power of the skill is greater than or equal to the power of a lock then it is unlocked. Only one attempt to pick a lock is permitted and it requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
            If the character is attempting to force a mechanical lock the power of this skill is <check type="str">Locks and Traps+2</check>. If the power of the skill is greater than or equal to the power of a lock then it is unlocked. If the power of the skill is less than the power of the lock then the lock is broken. A broken lock cannot be picked nor forced nor unlocked with the correct key. Forcing a lock requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
            When the <name>Observation</name> skill is used to search for traps the power of the skill becomes <check type="int">Observation+Locks and Traps</check>.
            If the character is attempting to disarm or set a trap the power of this skill is <check type="dex">Locks and Traps</check>. A sufficiently bad power when attempting to disarm a trap will set it off. To set a trap the right tools are needed and the power of the trap is equal to the power of this skill. Typically setting a trap takes around ten minutes.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>2</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Locks and Traps</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Unlock a lock of strength up to X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Power type="roll" stat="Str" add="2"><skill>Locks and Traps</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Force a lock of strength up to X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>2</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Locks and Traps</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Arm or disarm a trap of strength up to X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Lore</Name>
        <Stat>Int</Stat>
        <Cost>1</Cost>
        <Synergy>Lore</Synergy>
        <Text>
            A character with this skill is particularly knowledgable when it comes to divine lore.
            The character can attempt to remember knowledge with a cheock of power <check type="int">Lore</check>. Having access to a library or similar source will provide bonuses to this check.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Power type="roll" add="1"><skill>Lore</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Know about lore with power X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Lunge</Name>
        <Stat>Str</Stat>
        <Cost>3</Cost>
        <Synergy>Warrior</Synergy>
        <Text>
            With great power the character near instantly closes the distance to a foe landing on them with a crushing blow.
            This skill reduces fall damage. If the character falls <emph>X</emph> metres then they lose <HP>(X-Lunge-2)</HP> with a minimum of <HP>0</HP>.
            When jumping the power of the skill is <check type="str">Lunge+1</check>. The maximum vertical distance jumped is equal to the power in metres. The maximum horizontal distance jumped is equal to twice the power in metres. The character may choose to end the lunge in a standard <name>Attack</name>. If they do so the total power of the attack is equal to the sum of the power of the <name>Lunge</name> with the power of the <name>Attack</name>.
            If the character jumps less than the power of the jump in metres then the power of the skill is considered to be the length of the jump in metres for the purposes of ended in an <name>Attack</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Attack</Action>
            <Mana>2</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Lunge</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Lunge at someone gaining Lunge plus a standard attack to anyone within a distance of 2X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Observation</Name>
        <Stat>Int</Stat>
        <Cost>1</Cost>
        <Text>
            This character has honed their ability to see or hear even the smallest of details.
            The character can actively or passively noticing something visual or aural with a power of <check type="int">Observation+1</check>.
            They can perform unskilled <Int/> actions can be performed with a power of <check type="int">Observation+1</check>. Any skill with an <Int/> icon requires this skill.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Observation</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Observe with a power of X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
        <Effect>
            <Power type="roll" add="1"><skill>Observation</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Unskilled Int action with power X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Permanence</Name>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>5</Cost>
        <Spell>Oxdoro</Spell>
        <Synergy>Mechanist</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling the power of <name>Oxdoro</name> the character can take temporary energies and make them permanent.
            The power of this skill is <check type="fai">Permanence</check>. If the power of this skill is at least the power of a spell with ongoing mana costs the spell no longer requires the ongoing cost. However the caster of the ongoing spell reduces their <MPMax/> by twice the ongoing cost. If the skill required a <name>Major Action</name> to sustain it now requires a <name>Minor Action</name>. If the skill required a <name>Minor Action</name> to sustain it now requires no action to sustain.
        </Text>t
        <Effect>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Permanence</skill></Power>
            <Mana>5</Mana>
            <Quick>If X is at least the power of a spell, the caster gets -2X to max MP but pays no more MP.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Phase Shift</Name>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>2</Cost>
        <Spell>Oxdoro</Spell>
        <Synergy>Mechanist</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling the power of <name>Oxdoro</name> the character can slide slightly outside the realm of existence.
            The power of this skill is <check type="fai">Phase Shift</check>. The user can becomes <name>Ethereal</name> for a number of turns equal to the power of this skill. Casting requires a <name>Minor Action</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Phase Shift</skill></Power>
            <Duration>X</Duration>
            <Mana>5,1</Mana>
            <Quick>Become Ethereal.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Poison</Name>
        <Name>Cure Poison</Name>
        <Invert/>
        <Stat>Int</Stat>
        <Cost>3</Cost>
        <Synergy>Rogue</Synergy>
        <Text>
            The character has an intimate knowledge of poisons and their cures.
            When a character makes a successful standard Attack the defender is poisoned with power <check type="int">Poison</check>. If the character is using a piercing weapon then they have a bonus of +2 to their <name>Poison</name> roll.
            Alternatively a character may use a <name>Major Action</name> to cure a poison with power of <check type="int">Poison</check>. If the character is currently under the effects of a poison then the poison is reduced in power by the power of this skill. If a character is not under the effects of a poison but was poisoned within the last hour then the character can counteract the long term effects of a poison. For example the <name>Deep Wounds</name> caused by a poison.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Mana>2</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Poison</skill></Power>
            <Quick>After a successful attack target is poisoned for X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>2</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Cure Poison</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Reduce the strength of a poison by X or heal X deep wounds made by poison.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Poison Cloud</Name>
        <Require>Fog</Require>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>3</Cost>
        <Spell>Innodi</Spell>
        <Synergy>Necromancer</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Innodi</name> the character can summon a poisonous cloud that saps the energy from any creature caught inside.
            The power of this skill is <check type="fai">Poison Cloud</check>. The radius of the cloud is the power in metres. A <name>Poison Cloud</name> has all the properties of <name>Fog</name>. Any turn that a character ends while in the cloud must make a <check type="str">Endurance</check> or <check type="fai">Sense</check> check. If a character fails this check they are effected by <name>Poison</name> with a power equal to the power of the cloud.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>5,2</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Poison Cloud</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Create a cloud with strength X that poisons for X to anyone caught inside.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Poison Dart</Name>
        <Require>Divine Arrow</Require>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>2</Cost>
        <Spell>Innodi</Spell>
        <Synergy>Necromancer</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Innodi</name> the character summons an ethereal dart laced with poison.
            The power of this attack is <check type="fai">Poison Dart</check>. The target becomes <name>Poisoned</name> with power equal to the power of this attack.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Attack</Action>
            <Mana>4</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Poison Dart</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Attack for X. If successful it poisons for X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Portal</Name>
        <Require>Telekinesis</Require>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>3</Cost>
        <Spell>Oxdoro</Spell>
        <Synergy>Mechanist</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Oxdoro</name> the character is able to link disparate places in space to allow thoroughfare between them.
            When used to create a first portal this skill always succeeds and required a <name>Minor Action</name>.
            When used to create a portal that links to another portal the power of this skill is <check type="fai">Portal</check>. If the portal to be created is no further than two to the power of this skill in metres to an existing portal then the creation succeeds and the portals are linked as well as any other portals currently linked to the existing portal. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
            Any character may move into any portal and exit at any of its linked portals. The ongoing <MP/> cost of this skill is equal to the number of linked portals beyond the first. The character may at any time choose to close all the portals or for a <name>Minor Action</name> close a particular portal. Closing a portal does not affect the linked nature of any remaining portals no matter how they were originally created and linked. Portals cannot close while objects are passing through them. 
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>1</Mana>
            <Power>-</Power>
            <Quick>Create the first portal.</Quick>
        </Effect>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>1,X</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Portal</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Create a portal and link to an existing portal within 2 to the X metres. Ongoing cost is one less than the number of portals.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Precision Attack</Name>
        <Require>Attack</Require>
        <Stat>Dex</Stat>
        <Cost>2</Cost>
        <Synergy>Rogue</Synergy>
        <Text>
            The character has excellent knowledge of all creatures weak points and the training to strike at them.
            The power of this attack is <check type="dex" penalty="1">Attack+Precision Attack</check>. The damage is equal to the power of the attack. They may use a <name>Minor Action</name> to get an additional +1 to their skill check.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Attack</Action>
            <Mana>1</Mana>
            <Power type="roll" die="-1" weapon="1"><skill>Precision Attack</skill><skill>Attack</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Attack for X. Spend a Minor Action to get +1.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Raise Undead</Name>
        <Name>Hurt Undead</Name>
        <Require>Control Undead</Require>
        <Invert/>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>3</Cost>
        <Spell>Innodi</Spell>
        <Synergy>Necromancer</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Innodi</name> the character gives life to those who are recently departed.
            The power of this skill is <check type="fai">Raise Undead</check>. The caster can raise up to the power of this skill in levels of creatures who have recently died to create <name>Undead</name> warriors. No matter how many undead are raised the ongoing cost is always <MP>1</MP>.
            Any controlled undead can be dismissed for <MP>3</MP>. The caster gains <HP>1</HP> for each undead dismissed in this way.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>3,1</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Raise Undead</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Raise an undead with power X. Divide to raise an additional undead.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Redirect</Name>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>3</Cost>
        <Spell>Arthur</Spell>
        <Synergy>Battle Mage</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Arthur</name> the character is able to take a projectile and fire it back to its origin.
            The power of this skill is <check type="fai">Redirect</check>. If the power of the projectile attack is equal to or less than this power then the attack targets the attacker instead.
            This skill may be used to redirect a projectile targeting another character. The effect is the same however a <name>Minor Action</name> is required if used in this way.
            This skill may only be used on projectile attacks.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Defend</Action>
            <Mana>2</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Redirect</skill></Power>
            <Quick>If X is at least a projectile attack then the attack targets the attacker.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Refresh</Name>
        <Cost>5</Cost>
        <Synergy>Battle Mage</Synergy>
        <Text>
            The character has great propensity to renew mental energies.
            The character's refresh rate is equal to the level of this skill minus 5.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Power add="-10" times="0.5"><skill>Refresh</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Target gains MP at a rate of X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Regenerate</Name>
        <Cost>5</Cost>
        <Synergy>Warrior</Synergy>
        <Text>
            The character has great propensity to renew physical health.
            The character's regenerate rate is equal to half the level of this skill minus 5.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Power add="-10" times="0.5"><skill>Regenerate</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Target gains HP at a rate of X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Sense</Name>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>1</Cost>
        <Text>
            This character has honed their ability to sense to even minor changes in the world around them.
            Actively or passively noticing something non-visual and non-aural with power <check type="fai">Sense+1</check>.
            Unskilled <Fai/> actions can be performed with a power of <check type="fai">Sense+1</check>. Any skill with a <Fai/> icon requires this skill.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Power type="roll" add="1"><skill>Sense</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Sense with a power of X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
        <Effect>
            <Power type="roll" add="1"><skill>Sense</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Unskilled Fai action with power X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Sleep</Name>
        <Name>Wake</Name>
        <Require>Fear</Require>
        <Invert/>
        <Stat>Int</Stat>
        <Cost>2</Cost>
        <Spell>Ird'ken</Spell>
        <Synergy>Channeller</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Ird'ken</name> the caster can gain control over their state of consciousness.
            If trying to cause a character to sleep the power of this skill is <check type="fai">Sleep</check>. While under the influence of this skill the targeted character has their <HP/> lowered by power of this skill for the purposes of consciousness and unconsciousness. Note that this does not affect at what <HP/> a character dies, only when they fall unconscious or regain consciousness. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
            If trying to wake an unconscious character the power is <name>Wake</name>. For the duration of this skill the character has their <HP/> raised by the power of this skill for the purposes of consciousness and unconsciousness. Note this does not affect at what <HP/> a character dies, only when they fall unconscious or regain consciousness. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>3,1</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Sleep</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Target gains or loses X to their HP for the purposes of consciousness</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Spell Shield</Name>
        <Require>Counter-spell</Require>
        <Stat>Int</Stat>
        <Cost>2</Cost>
        <Synergy>Channeller</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By interjecting in the target's commune with their deity the character skilfully disrupts the flow of power rendering the divine power completely ineffective.
            The power of this skill is <check type="int">Spell Shield</check>. If the power of this skill is equal to or greater than the power of any spell just cast then all the effects of that spell do not occur. A countered spell stills requires it's casting cost although no ongoing costs are required. Casting requires a <name>Minor Action</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>7</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Spell Shield</skill></Power>
            <Quick>If X is at least the power of a spell it is countered.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Sprint</Name>
        <Stat>Dex</Stat>
        <Cost>1</Cost>
        <Text>
            This character is particularly agile and can move with grace and speed.
            The character can move <check type="dex">Sprint</check>+2 metres every turn. This check is only made once per combat.
            Unskilled <Dex/> actions can be performed with a power of <check type="dex">Sprint+1</check>. Any skill with an <Dex/> icon requires this skill.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Sprint</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Character can move at X+2 metres/turn.</Quick>
        </Effect>
        <Effect>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Sprint</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Character can jump 2X+1 horizontally or X vertically</Quick>
        </Effect>
        <Effect>
            <Power type="roll" add="1"><skill>Sprint</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Unskilled Dex action with power X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Stealth</Name>
        <Stat>Dex</Stat>
        <Cost>2</Cost>
        <Synergy>Rogue</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By staying in the shadows and sensing others movements around them the character can remain unseen.
            If hiding the power of this skill is <check type="dex">Stealth+2</check>. As long as this power is larger then a passive <name>Observation</name> check by those around them they remain hidden. For the duration that the user remains hidden only one roll is made. Hiding requires a <name>Minor Action</name>.
            If stealthily moving the power of this skill is <check type="dex">Stealth+1</check>. As long as this power is larger then a passive <name>Observation</name> check by those around them they remain hidden. For the duration that the user remains hidden only one roll is made. While moving this skill costs <MP>1</MP> to sustain. A character may stop moving to avoid paying this cost. Stealthy movement requries a <name>Minor Action</name>.
            If picking someone's pocket this skill has power of <check type="dex">Stealth</check>. If this is greater than a passive <name>Observation</name> check by the target then the item is stolen. This action costs <MP>5</MP> and requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>1</Mana>
            <Power type="roll" add="2"><skill>Stealth</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Hide with power X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>1,1</Mana>
            <Power type="roll" add="1"><skill>Stealth</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Move stealthily with power X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>5</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Stealth</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Pick pocket with power X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Steal Spell</Name>
        <Require>Inversion</Require>
        <Stat>Int</Stat>
        <Cost>1</Cost>
        <Synergy>Channeller</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By incredible skill the character interjects into a caster's commune with their deity they gain complete control of the spell, wielding it in any way they choose.
            The power of this skill is <check type="int">Steal Spell</check>. If this is greater than or equal to the power of a spell that has just been cast then the spell targets whoever the character wishes, if invertible they may invert the spell and if <name>Dividable</name> they may divide it. The power of the spell becomes the power of this skill. The casting cost is paid by the caster but the user may pay the ongoing costs to increase its duration in the same way that the original caster could. This skill requires a <name>Minor Action</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Minor</Action>
            <Mana>10</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Steal Spell</skill></Power>
            <Quick>If X is at least the power of a spell it becomes power X cast by this character.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Stun Attack</Name>
        <Require>Attack</Require>
        <Stat>Str</Stat>
        <Cost>2</Cost>
        <Synergy>Rogue</Synergy>
        <Text>
            The character moves with quick strikes that, while doing no damage, confounds the target and stun them for a short period.
            This attack has a power of <check type="str">Stun Attack</check>. The power of this attack is reduced by the defence skill used regardless of which defence skill is used. The defender is stunned for a number of turns equal to the remaining power of this skill.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Attack</Action>
            <Mana>3</Mana>
            <Power type="roll" weapon="1"><skill>Stun Attack</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Attack for X. All defence skills reduce X. Stun for X turns.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Stunning Bolt</Name>
        <Require>Divine Arrow</Require>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>4</Cost>
        <Spell>Loreanna</Spell>
        <Synergy>Trickster</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Loreanna</name> the character is able to sum- mon a divine bolt which confounds whomever it strikes.
            The power of this attack is <check type="fai">Stunning Bolt</check>. The power of this attack is reduced by the defence skill regardless of which skill is used. The target is <name>Stun</name>ned for a number of turns equal to its power.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Attack</Action>
            <Mana>3</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Stunning Bolt</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Attack for X. All defence skills reduce X. Stun for X turns.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Switch</Name>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>2</Cost>
        <Spell>Loreanna</Spell>
        <Synergy>Trickster</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Loreanna</name> the character is able to channel the energy of others to transfer each to the other.
            The power of this skill is <check type="fai">Switch</check>. This skill fails if the distance between the targets in metres is greater than the power of this skill. This skill also fails if the difference between the targets' <HP/> is greater than the power of this skill. The targets are now each standing where the other was standing. Also their <HP/> has switched. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
            Note that this skill may raise a character's <HP/> above their <HPMax/>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>5</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Switch</skill></Power>
            <Quick>If X is greater than the HP difference and distance of two characters then they swap position and HP.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Taunt</Name>
        <Stat>Int</Stat>
        <Cost>3</Cost>
        <Synergy>Warrior</Synergy>
        <Text>
            This character has the ability to provoke their opponents into relentlessly attacking.
            The power of this skill is <check type="int">Taunt</check>. Any opposing character within a radius equal to the power of this skill in metres and <MP/> less than twice the power of this skill must attack this character in their next turn. Taunting requires a <name>Minor Action</name> but the character may use defence skills as normal this turn.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Minor</Action>
            <Mana>1</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Taunt</skill></Power>
            <Quick>All characters with at most 2X MP must attack the character.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Telekinesis</Name>
        <Stat>Int</Stat>
        <Cost>2</Cost>
        <Spell>Oxdoro</Spell>
        <Synergy>Mechanist</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Oxdoro</name> the caster can deftly manoeuvre small objects or crudely move large objects from a distance.
            If used to manipulate small objects this skill has power equal to <third/> of its level. For a cost of <MP>1</MP> per turn the character can telekinetically move objects with precision. Each unit of power enables the character to move an additional 10kg. For example with a skill level of 10 the power of this skill is 3 and so the character can manipulate objects with mass up to 30kg. Delicate movement requries a <name>Major Action</name> but no <MP/>.
            If used to crudely move large objects the power of this skill is given by <check type="int">Telekinesis</check>. The mana cost is <MP>5</MP>. If the power of this skill is P and M is the mass of the object to be moved in kg then the object is moved a distance D in metres given by the equation below.
            <equation> D = \frac{P \times 20kg}{M} </equation>
            If a creature is thrown in the above way into a wall or similar barrier then they are stunned for a number of turns equal to the extra distance they would have been thrown. For example a 60kg character is thrown with a Telekinesis check of power 12 and so would be thrown 4m. They hit a wall after 1m and so they are then stunned for 3 turns. Gross movement requires a <name>Minor Action</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Minor</Action>
            <Mana>1,1</Mana>
            <Power><skill>Telekinesis</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Precisely Move objects of up to 3X kg</Quick>
        </Effect>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>5</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Telekinesis</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Move a large object (20X kg/weight) metres.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Track</Name>
        <Stat>Int</Stat>
        <Cost>2</Cost>
        <Synergy>Rogue</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By careful examination of the environment via visual and olfactory cues a character is able to track a creature path over any terrain.
            The power of the skill is <check type="int">Track</check>. The power of the skill provides how deftly the character can follow the track. With a power of two or greater the track can be followed albeit slowly. With a power of four or more the track can be followed at more or less walking pace. With a power of six or more the track can be followed at a running pace. Tracking requires a <name>Major Action</name> for each turn spent tracking.
            The <name>Track</name> roll is modified by several penalties. A path that has been made in the past day has no penalty. However there is a penalty of -1 for each day beyond the first. Soft ground provides no penalty. However there is a penalty of up to -3 relative to the hardness of the ground.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>3</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Track</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Track with power X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Unlock</Name>
        <Name>Lock</Name>
        <Invert/>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>3</Cost>
        <Spell>Ird'ken</Spell>
        <Synergy>Channeller</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Ird'ken</name> the caster is able to open any passage or bar any door.
            If used to unlock a divine or mechanical lock the power of this skill is given by <check type="fai">Unlock</check>. If the power of this skill is greater than the power of a lock then it is unlocked. Casting requires a <name>Minor Action</name>.
            If used to lock a barrier, such as a door or chest, the power of this skill is <check type="fai">Unlock</check>. Such a barrier becomes locked with a divine lock of power equal to the power of this skill. If the barrier already has a divine lock then the power of the divine lock becomes equal to the maximum of its current power and the power of this skill. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
            Locks can be both mechanical and divine. This skill attempts to unlock both with a single roll and can succeed to unlock one but fail to unlock the other.
            Multiple characters can pool their rolls when attempting either to lock or unlock a barrier.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>3</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Unlock</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Lock or unlock magically for strength X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Void</Name>
        <Require>Counter-spell</Require>
        <Stat>Int</Stat>
        <Cost>3</Cost>
        <Spell>Ird'ken</Spell>
        <Synergy>Channeller</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Ird'ken</name> the power of any ongoing divine effect is sapped.
            The power of this skill is <check type="int">Void</check>. Any ongoing divine effect within a radius equal to the power of this skill in metres has its power reduced by the power of this skill to a minimum of zero. If the power of a divine skill reaches zero it is immediately cancelled and no ongoing effects or costs are applied. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
            This spell may be continued. If so then every spell either cast within the <name>Void</name> or targeted into the <name>Void</name> has its power reduced by the power of the original <name>Void</name> check. Ongoing costs are <MP>2</MP> and a <name>Minor Action</name>.
            This skill has no effect on a <name>Divine Contract</name> unless it specifically targets the contract in which case it does not have the above effect. The contract is immediately activated however it uses <check type="int">Void<times/>2</check> fewer dice. A character may not maliciously use this skill on a <name>Divine Contract</name> in an attempt to trigger this effect.
            Note that this effect applies to the effects of a spell and not casters. This means that the targets must be in the radius of this skill and not the casters. This skill can affect some characters but not others from a single spell and the caster of the original spell may choose to pay the ongoing cost for the remaining targets.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>5,2</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Void</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Cancel ongoing effects and new spells with power less than X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Will of Arthur</Name>
        <Require>Follower of Arthur</Require>
        <Invert/>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>10</Cost>
        <Spell>Arthur</Spell>
        <Text>
            As a devout follower of <name>Arthur</name> the caster is able to draw extreme divine power from <name>Arthur</name>. They can increase the potency of all attack or defence abilities in their presence.
            The power of this skill is <check type="fai">Will of Arthur</check>. The duration of this skill is equal to its power in turns. The caster chooses either attack or defence or both and all skills of that type/those types are increased by the power of this skill in all characters near the caster.
            If the caster chooses to increase both attack and defence skills then this skill is not considered to be invertible for that casting. If only one is used then the other is considered the inverse.
            This skill is unaffected by <name>Counter-spell</name>, <name>Spell Shield</name>, <name>Inversion</name>, <name>Steal Spell</name> and <name>Void</name>. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>M</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Will of Arthur</skill></Power>
            <Duration>X</Duration>
            <Quick>Add or remove X to all attack skills, defence skills or both.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Will of Innodi</Name>
        <Require>Follower of Innodi</Require>
        <Invert/>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>10</Cost>
        <Spell>Innodi</Spell>
        <Text>
            As a devout follower of <name>Innodi</name> the caster is able to draw extreme divine power from <name>Innodi</name>. They can channel life force in or out of the surrounding environment healing or grievously harming those around them.
            The power of this skill is <check type="fai">Will of Innodi</check>. Every character near the caster, including the caster, either gains a number of <name>Deep Wounds</name> equal to the power of this skill or heals a number of <name>Deep Wounds</name> equal to the power of this skill. Any character that is healed but has fewer <name>Deep Wounds</name> than the power of this skill gains the rest in <HP/>. This is not an attack skill and so cannot be defended against.
            This skill is unaffected by <name>Counter-spell</name>, <name>Spell Shield</name>, <name>Inversion</name>, <name>Steal Spell</name> and <name>Void</name>. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>M</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Will of Innodi</skill></Power>
            <Quick>All characters gain or lose X deep wounds.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Will of Ird'ken</Name>
        <Require>Follower of Ird'ken</Require>
        <Invert/>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>10</Cost>
        <Spell>Ird'ken</Spell>
        <Text>
            As a devout follower of <name>Ird'ken</name> the caster is able to draw extreme divine power from <name>Ird'ken</name> to cause chaos or order.
            The power of this skill is <check type="fai">Follower of Ird'ken</check>. The duration of this skill is equal to its power in turns. The caster chooses to produce chaos or order. If used to produce order then every character nearby chooses one attack skill, one defence skill and one other skill. The other skill may be an attack skill or a defence skill. For the duration of the <name>Will of Ird'ken</name> they may not use any other skills. If used to produce chaos then players no longer choose which skills they use. During their turn each character randomly chooses one of their skills that uses a <name>Major Action</name> and has a chance to succeed. The specifics of the used skill, such as targets etc, are up to the character. When a target defends they randomly choose a defence skill that will result in at least one die rolled and must defend with that skill.
            This skill is unaffected by <name>Counter-spell</name>, <name>Spell Shield</name>, <name>Inversion</name>, <name>Steal Spell</name> and <name>Void</name>. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>M</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Will of Ird'ken</skill></Power>
            <Duration>X</Duration>
            <Quick>All character either act randomly or only have one attack one defence and one other skill they can use.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Will of Loreanna</Name>
        <Require>Follower of Loreanna</Require>
        <Invert/>
        <Divide/>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>10</Cost>
        <Spell>Loreanna</Spell>
        <Text>
            As a devout follower of <name>Loreanna</name> the caster is able to draw extreme divine power from <name>Loreanna</name>. The skill and luck of those around the caster become warped.
            The power of this skill is <check type="fai">Will of Loreanna</check>. The caster chooses to either increase every skill performed nearby to increase by one die type or decrease every skill performed nearby for one die type. This effect is <name>Dividable</name> so by reducing the duration the caster can increase the number of die levels gained or lost.
            This skill is unaffected by <name>Counter-spell</name>, <name>Spell Shield</name>, <name>Inversion</name>, <name>Steal Spell</name> and <name>Void</name>. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>M</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Will of Loreanna</skill></Power>
            <Duration>X</Duration>
            <Quick>All skills get +1 or -1. Divide to give additional +1 or -1.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Will of Oxdoro</Name>
        <Require>Follower of Oxdoro</Require>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>10</Cost>
        <Spell>Oxdoro</Spell>
        <Text>
            As a devout follower of <name>Oxdoro</name> the caster is able to draw extreme divine power from <name>Oxdoro</name>. They can stop time for everyone except themselves bringing objects and creatures back to life by their touch.
            The power of this skill is <check type="fai">Will of Oxdoro</check>. The world is frozen in time for duration equal to this skill's power in turns. Any character, including the caster, who has this skill at a level equal to or greater than the power of this skill is not frozen. Any object touched by an unfrozen character, including other characters, becomes unfrozen. When frozen character cannot defend however any attack on them will unfreeze them.
            This skill is unaffected by <name>Counter-spell</name>, <name>Spell Shield</name>, <name>Inversion</name>, <name>Steal Spell</name> and <name>Void</name>. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>M</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Will of Oxdoro</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Freeze everything but characters with the Will of Oxdoro. Anything they touch unfreezes.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Will of Travaer</Name>
        <Require>Follower of Travaer</Require>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>10</Cost>
        <Spell>Travaer</Spell>
        <Text>
            As a devout follower of <name>Travaer</name> the caster is able to draw extreme divine power from <name>Travaer</name>. The caster can invert any spell or skill used in their presence.
            The power of this skill is <name>Will of Travaer</name>. The duration of this skill is equal to its power in turns. If any invertible spell or skill is used near this skill's user, this skill's user can, at their discretion, take it's inverse ability.
            This only affects newly activated skills and does not affect ongoing effects. This can affect the will of other deities.
            This skill is unaffected by <name>Counter-spell</name>, <name>Spell Shield</name>, <name>Inversion</name>, <name>Steal Spell</name> and <name>Void</name>. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>. While this skill does not have a divine token, it is a spell.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>M</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Will of Travaer</skill></Power>
            <Duration>X</Duration>
            <Quick>Caster gets the chance to invert any invertible spell.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Ability>
        <Name>Acrobatic</Name>
        <Synergy>Rogue</Synergy>
        <Text>
            This character is highly agile and dextrous. They may make a <check type="dex">Sprint</check> to perform an acrobatic action.
            If appropriate an <name>Acrobatic</name> character may help another character perform an acrobatic action. If they do so it requires a <name>Major Action</name> for each turn that they assist. A <check type="dex">Sprint</check> is made with the <name>Sprint</name> skill of the assisting character and the <Dex/> of the assisted character.
            Acrobatic characters have two <name>Minor Action</name>s each turn.
        </Text>
        <Quick>The character is unusually agile and has two Minor Actions each turn.</Quick>
    </Ability>
    
    <Ability>
        <Name>Ambidextrous</Name>
        <Synergy>Rogue</Synergy>
        <Text>
            This character is just as able with their off hand. They may They may dual wield one handed weapons with the same <name>Damage Type</name>. When dual wielding a character adds the bonus from both weapons when making their <name>Attack</name> rolls.
        </Text>
        <Quick>The character is just as able with their off hand and may dual wield.</Quick>
    </Ability>
    
    <Ability>
        <Name>Atheist</Name>
        <Text>
            An Atheist has made the choice to divorce themselves from the gods. The character gains <name>Magical Resistance</name> of 1. An <name>Atheist</name> may not cast spells.
            The presence of the Gods is irrefutable and so an Atheist believes not in the non-existence of Gods but that they should not be followed. This ability should affect how a character is role-played.
        </Text>
        <Quick>Magic Resistance +1. The character cannot cast spells.</Quick>
    </Ability>
    
    <Ability>
        <Name>Blacksmith</Name>
        <Text>
            The character is a skilled blacksmith and can forge their own weapons, armour and miscellanea given the right equipment and a forge.
            When making items a <check type="int">Observation</check> is made which determines the <name>Quality</name> of the item made. A pass gives a normal <name>Quality</name> with each result range adding or subtracting 1 from the <name>Quality</name>
        </Text>
        <Quick>Make and Observation roll to make weapons and armour.</Quick>
    </Ability>

    <Ability>
        <Name>Carpenter</Name>
        <Text>
            This character is skilled at carpentry and can build and analyse wooden structures.
            They may make a <check type="dex">Sprint</check> to build a wooden structure. They may make a <check type="int">Observation</check> to analyse a wooden structure.
        </Text>
        <Quick>This character is skilled at carpentry.</Quick>
    </Ability>
    
    <Ability>
        <Name>Chef</Name>
        <Text>
            This character is skilled at preparing and cooking food.
            They may <check type="int">Observation</check> to make or prepare food. This includes the ability to butcher animals and collect food in wilderness areas.
        </Text>
        <Quick>This character is skilled at cooking.</Quick>
    </Ability>
    
    <Ability>
        <Name>Emote</Name>
        <Synergy>Lore</Synergy>
        <Text>
            This character can win arguments through reassurance, flattery or other emotional means.
            They can make a <check type="int">Sense</check> to start a <name>Debate</name>.
        </Text>
        <Quick>Emotional argument with Sense/Int check.</Quick>
    </Ability>
    
    <Ability>
        <Name>Equestrianism</Name>
        <Text>
            This character is a lover of horses and a skilled rider.
            They can ride horses without checks. To attack from a horse a <check type="dex">Sprint</check> is made and the attack has strength of the minimum of this check and the attack roll. If a melee weapon was used and the horse charging add +5 to the result.
        </Text>
        <Quick>Can ride horses and attack from horseback.</Quick>
    </Ability>
    
    <Ability>
        <Name>Follower of Arthur</Name>
        <Synergy>Battle Mage</Synergy>
        <Require><XP type="Spell">50</XP></Require>
        <Text>
            This character is a devout follower of <name>Arthur</name> and has dedicated their life to the deity <name>Arthur</name>.
            They gain +2 to all spells provided by <name>Arthur</name> but -1 to all spells provided by other gods. This choice of deity should affect character driven traits.
            A character cannot become a <name>Follower of Arthur</name> if they already follow another god.
        </Text>
        <Quick>+2 to Arthur spells -1 to others.</Quick>
    </Ability>
    
    <Ability>
        <Name>Follower of Innodi</Name>
        <Synergy>Necromancer</Synergy>
        <Require><XP type="Spell">50</XP></Require>
        <Text>
            This characer is a devout follower of <name>Innodi</name> and has dedicated their life to the deity <name>Innodi</name>.
            They gain +2 to all spells provided by <name>Innodi</name> but -1 to all spells provided by other gods. This choice of deity should affect character driven traits.
            A character cannot become a <name>Follower of Innodi</name> if they already follow another god.
        </Text>
        <Quick>+2 to Innodi spells -1 to others.</Quick>
    </Ability>
    
    <Ability>
        <Name>Follower of Ird'ken</Name>
        <Synergy>Channeller</Synergy>
        <Require><XP type="Spell">50</XP></Require>
        <Text>
            This character is a devout follower of <name>Ird'ken</name> and has dedicated their life to the deity <name>Ird'ken</name>.
            They gain +2 to all spells provided by <name>Ird'ken</name> but -1 to all spells provided by other gods. This choice of deity should affect character driven traits.
            A character cannot become a <name>Follower of Ird'ken</name> if they already follow another god.
        </Text>
        <Quick>+2 to Ird'ken spells -1 to others.</Quick>
    </Ability>
    
    <Ability>
        <Name>Follower of Loreanna</Name>
        <Synergy>Trickster</Synergy>
        <Require><XP type="Spell">50</XP></Require>
        <Text>
            This character is a devout follower of <name>Loreanna</name> and has dedicated their life to the deity <name>Loreanna</name>.
            They gain +2 to all spells provided by <name>Loreanna</name> but -1 to all spells provided by other gods. This choice of deity should affect character driven traits.
            A character cannot become a <name>Follower of Loreanna</name> if they already follow another god.
        </Text>
        <Quick>+2 to Loreanna spells -1 to others.</Quick>
    </Ability>
    
    <Ability>
        <Name>Follower of Oxdoro</Name>
        <Synergy>Mechanist</Synergy>
        <Require><XP type="Spell">50</XP></Require>
        <Text>
            This character is a devout follower of <name>Oxdoro</name> and has dedicated their life to the deity <name>Oxdoro</name>. They gain +2 to all spells provided by <name>Oxdoro</name> but -1 to all spells provided by other gods. This choice of deity should affect character driven traits.
            A character cannot become a <name>Follower of Oxdoro</name> if they already follow another god.
        </Text>
        <Quick>+2 to Oxdoro spells -1 to others.</Quick>
    </Ability>
    
    <Ability>
        <Name>Follower of Travaer</Name>
        <Require><XP type="Spell">50</XP></Require>
        <Text>
            This character is a devout follower of <name>Travaer</name> and has dedicated their life to the deity <name>Travaer</name>.
            They gain +1 to all invertible spells but -1 to all non-invertible spells. This choice of deity should affect character driven traits.
            A character cannot become a <name>Follower of Travaer</name> if they already follow another god.
        </Text>
        <Quick>+1 to invertible spells. -1 to non-invertible spells.</Quick>
    </Ability>
    
    <Ability>
        <Name>Gadgeteer</Name>
        <Synergy>Mechanist</Synergy>
        <Text>
            This character loves to tinker and experiment with mechanical devices.
            Given the right tools this character knows how to build and repair small gadgets or any mechanical device with either a <check type="dex">Sprint</check> or <check type="int">Observation</check>.
            This character receives a +2 to <name>Locks and Traps</name> which does not apply when forcing locks.
        </Text>
        <Quick>Skilled with gadgets.</Quick>
    </Ability>
    
    <Ability>
        <Name>Gambler</Name>
        <Synergy>Trickster</Synergy>
        <Text>
            A <name>Gambler</name> knows how to twist the fates to their will and when to leave good enough alone.
            They are able to make an <check type="int">Observation</check> to assess risks. They know all games of chance and have a greatly increased chance of winning.
        </Text>
        <Quick>Good as gambling. Can assess risks.</Quick>
    </Ability>
    
    <Ability>
        <Name>Imbue</Name>
        <Require>Orb Crafter</Require>
        <Text>
            By calling on divine powers an item can be imbued with the magics of an Orb or an Orb can be created by removing the divine powers of a magical item.
            When used to imbue an item with and Orb the power is <check type="fai">Sense<times/>2</check>. If the power of the skill is at least the power of the Orb then the item gains the properties of the Orb and the Orb is destroyed. If the power of the skill is less than the power of the Orb, the item already has magical properties, or the item is not compatible with the orb, then nothing happens. However if the power of the skill is zero then the Orb is destroyed.
            When used to extract properties from an item the power of this ability is <check type="fai">Extract<times/>2</check>. If the power of the ability is at least as powerful as the item's magics then the item loses its magical properties and an Orb with the properties is created. If the power of the skill is less than the power of the item's magics then nothing happens. However if the power of the skill is zero then the item loses its magical properties but no Orb is produced.
            Depending on the skill of the crafter these processes can take hours to perform. Note that while divine powers are called upon, this is not a spell.
        </Text>
        <Quick>Imbue or Extract Orbs from items.</Quick>
    </Ability>
    
    <Ability>
        <Name>Intimidate</Name>
        <Synergy>Warrior</Synergy>
        <Text>
            This character can win arguments through intimidation and aggression.
            They can make a <check type="int">Endurance</check> to start a <name>Debate</name>.
        </Text>
        <Quick>Intimidate using an Endurance/Int check.</Quick>
    </Ability>
    
    <Ability>
        <Name>Iron Will</Name>
        <Text>
            A character with an <name>Iron Will</name> can focus their mental energies to provide a temporary bonus to any task they can perform.
            They may use a <name>Minor Action</name> when they use a skill and spend <MP>X</MP> to increase their level in that skill by X for that usage. This perk may not be used with the will of a deity.
        </Text>
        <Quick>Spend X MP to gain +X to a skill.</Quick>
    </Ability>
    
    <Ability>
        <Name>Leader</Name>
        <Require><XP>250</XP></Require>
        <Text>
            This character is a born leader. This <name>Ability</name> unlocks leadership skills.
        </Text>
        <Quick>Unlocks leadership skills.</Quick>
    </Ability>
    
    <Ability>
        <Name>Literate</Name>
        <Synergy>Lore</Synergy>
        <Text>
            This character knows how to read and write.
        </Text>
        <Quick>Can read and write.</Quick>
    </Ability>
    
    <Ability>
        <Name>Mana Shield</Name>
        <Text>
            A character with a mana shield may take all damage from one source to their <MP/> instead of <HP/>. If this would reduce their <MP/> below zero then it reduces their <MP/> to zero and the rest of the damage goes to their <HP/> instead. For the purposes of all skills and effects mana shield damage is considered <HP/> damage.
        </Text>
        <Quick>May take damage to MP instead of HP.</Quick>
    </Ability>
    
    <Ability>
        <Name>Mason</Name>
        <Text>
            This character is skilled at masonry. They may make a <check type="dex">Sprint</check> to mason a structure. They may make a <check type="int">Observation</check> to analyse masonry.
        </Text>
        <Quick>This character is skilled at masonry.</Quick>
    </Ability>
    
    <Ability>
        <Name>Orb Crafter</Name>
        <Text>
            By calling on divine powers the caster can create a magical Orb.
            When creating orbs the power of this ability is <check type="fai">Sense</check>. If the power of the ability is at least the required power for the type of Orb then an Orb is created of the desired type and power. Note that this is a spell with the deity dependent on the type of Orb.
            When combining orbs the power of this ability is <check type="fai">Sense</check>. If the power of this ability is at least the sum of the component Orbs then a new Orb is created with the combined properties of the component Orbs and power equal to the sum of the component Orbs. If the power of the ability is less than the sum of the component Orbs then nothing happens. However if there is a critical failure then all the component Orbs are destroyed.
            Note that while it is possible for the properties to cancel the resultant power is still the sum of the component Orbs. Creating an Orb is a spell and the deity depends on the Orb created.
        </Text>
        <Quick>Can craft orbs with magical properties.</Quick>
    </Ability>
    
    <Ability>
        <Name>Pocket Dimension</Name>
        <Synergy>Mechanist</Synergy>
        <Text>
            A character with Pocket Dimension has enough swing with <name>Oxdoro</name> that they can warp space sufficiently to create a pocket to store small materials in. The pocket is a rectangular prism with a maximum volume of 8,000 cubic cm and no side less than 1cm. Note that a cube with 20cm sides gives 8,000 cubic cm.
        </Text>
        <Quick>Can make a pocket dimension of up to 20x20x20 cub. cm</Quick>
    </Ability>
    
    <Ability>
        <Name>Poison Resistant</Name>
        <Text>
            A character who is resistant to poison suffers from being <name>Poison</name>ed for half the duration. While the power of most poisons decreases by one each turn when someone with this perk is poisoned the poison decreases by two each turn.
        </Text>
        <Quick>Doubles recovery rate from poisons.</Quick>
    </Ability>
    
    <Ability>
        <Name>Quick Changer</Name>
        <Require>Wolf</Require>
        <Text>
            A wolf that can quickly change requires only a <name>Minor Action</name> to change between human form and wolf form. Changing to or from warg form for the first time in a turn does not require a <name>Minor Action</name>.
        </Text>
        <Quick>Change between wolf forms faster.</Quick>
    </Ability>
    
    <Ability>
        <Name>Sailor</Name>
        <Text>
            This character is born to ride the seas. They know what to watch for with sea weather and how to navigate and may make a <check type="int">Observation</check> to verify. They are also able to make minor seaworthy vessels with a <check type="dex">Sprint</check>.
        </Text>
        <Quick>The character is a skilled sailor</Quick>
    </Ability>
    
    <Ability>
        <Name>Reason</Name>
        <Synergy>Rogue</Synergy>
        <Text>
            This character can win arguments through intellectual debate.
            They can make a <check type="int">Observation</check> to start a <name>Debate</name>.
        </Text>
        <Quick>Rational argument with Observation check.</Quick>
    </Ability>
    
    <Ability>
        <Name>Silent Speech</Name>
        <Synergy>Channeller</Synergy>
        <Text>
            The character can reach into the minds of those around them to create a passage of communication for all those joined while providing protection from others to notice.
            Anyone joined can communicate to anyone else in the union with any language that they understand and the listeners understand. This is independent of what form a character is in. For example two characters in Wolf Form can use Silent Speech to talk to each other in common however they can only use divine if both characters can understand it.
            Minds can be joined if the parties are within 1km of the caster.
        </Text>
        <Quick>Can join minds to talk over short distances.</Quick>
    </Ability>
    
    <Ability>
        <Name>Streetwise</Name>
        <Synergy>Rogue</Synergy>
        <Text>
            This character knows a guy who knows a guy. They may make a [Observation:Int] check to find information.
        </Text>
        <Quick>Make an Observation check to know information.</Quick>
    </Ability>
    
    <Ability>
        <Name>Swimmer</Name>
        <Text>
            This character can swim. They may make a <check type="dex">Sprint</check> to perform an aquatic action.
            They may make a <check type="dex">Sprint</check> to hold their breath for an extended duration. A basic pass equates to 2 minutes, pass gives 5 minutes, prodigious pass gives 10 minutes and an epic pass gives 30 minutes.
        </Text>
        <Quick>Character is skilled at swimming and can hold their breath for extended periods.</Quick>
    </Ability>
    
    <Ability>
        <Name>Tough Fighter</Name>
        <Synergy>Warrior</Synergy>
        <Text>
            A <name>Tough Fighter</name> is used to being knocked around in combat and so is stunned for one fewer turns whenever they are stunned.
        </Text>
        <Quick>Stun for one turn fewer.</Quick>
    </Ability>
    
    <Ability>
        <Name>Weapons: Small</Name>
        <Synergy>Warrior</Synergy>
        <Text>
            This character knows how to effectively wield small weapons such as daggers. They gain +1 to <name>Attack</name> rolls and may use <Dex/> instead of <Str/>.
        </Text>
        <Quick>Wield daggers etc. with +1 and may use Dex instead of Str.</Quick>
    </Ability>
    
    <Ability>
        <Name>Weapons: Medium</Name>
        <Synergy>Warrior</Synergy>
        <Text>
            This character knows how to wield medium and large sized weaponry. They are allowed to use single and double handed weapons.
        </Text>
        <Quick>May wield one and two handed melee weapons.</Quick>
    </Ability>
    
    <Ability>
        <Name>Weapons: Large</Name>
        <Synergy>Warrior</Synergy>
        <Require>Weapons: Medium</Require>
        <Text>
            This character knows how to wield large weapons and can wield any two handed weapons as a one handed weapon. If they are also <name>Ambidextrous</name> they may dual wield two handed weapons.
        </Text>
        <Quick>May wield two handed weapons as if they were one handed weapons.</Quick>
    </Ability>
    
    <Ability>
        <Name>Weapons: Ranged</Name>
        <Synergy>Warrior</Synergy>
        <Text>
            This character knows how to wield ranged weapons such as bows and crossbows.
        </Text>
        <Quick>May wield bows and crossbows.</Quick>
    </Ability>
    
    <Ability>
        <Name>Were-Bear</Name>
        <Require>Urgan Elite</Require>
        <Text>
            A were-bear can transform to and from bear form from warg form using a <name>Minor Action</name>. They can transform between bear form and either human form or wolf form with a <name>Major Action</name> or a <name>Minor Action</name> if they have the <name>Quick Changer</name> perk.
        </Text>
        <Quick>Allows bear form.</Quick>
    </Ability>
    
    <Ability>
        <Name>Woodsman</Name>
        <Text>
            A character with this Ability is skilled in any outdoor environment. They receive no penalties from natural environmental sources. They know where to find food and other resources in the wild.
        </Text>
        <Quick>Good at outdoor survival.</Quick>
    </Ability>
    
    <Armour>
        <Name>Cloth</Name>
        <Effect></Effect>
    </Armour>
    
    <Armour>
        <Name>Leather</Name>
        <Require><Str>6</Str></Require>
        <Effect>
            <DR>1</DR>
            <Dex>-1</Dex>
        </Effect>
        <Quick>DR 1, Dex -1</Quick>
    </Armour>
    
    <Armour>
        <Name>Chain</Name>
        <Require><Str>8</Str></Require>
        <Effect>
            <DR>2</DR>
            <Dex>-2</Dex>
        </Effect>
        <Quick>DR 2, Dex -2</Quick>
    </Armour>
    
    <Armour>
        <Name>Plate</Name>
        <Require><Str>10</Str></Require>
        <Effect>
            <DR>3</DR>
            <Dex>-3</Dex>
        </Effect>
        <Quick>DR 3, Dex -3</Quick>
    </Armour>

    <Shield>
        <Name>Buckler</Name>
        <Effect><DR>1</DR></Effect>
        <Quick>DR 1</Quick>
    </Shield>
    
    <Shield>
        <Name>Tower Shield</Name>
        <Require><Str>8</Str></Require>
        <Require><Dex>6</Dex></Require>
        <Effect><DR>2</DR></Effect>
        <Quick>DR 2</Quick>
    </Shield>
    
    <Weapon>
        <Name>Dagger</Name>
        <Hands>1</Hands>
        <Class>Small</Class>
        <Damage>Piercing</Damage>
    </Weapon>

    <Weapon>
        <Name>Claws</Name>
        <Hands>2</Hands>
        <Class>Misc</Class>
        <Damage>Slashing</Damage>
    </Weapon>

    <Weapon>
        <Name>Short Sword</Name>
        <Require><Str>6</Str></Require>
        <Hands>1</Hands>
        <Class>Medium</Class>
        <Damage>Slashing</Damage>
        <Bonus>2</Bonus>
    </Weapon>
        
    <Weapon>
        <Name>Claymore</Name>
        <Require><Str>8</Str></Require>
        <Hands>2</Hands>
        <Class>Large</Class>
        <Damage>Slashing</Damage>
        <Bonus>3</Bonus>
    </Weapon>
    
    <Weapon>
        <Name>Battle Axe</Name>
        <Require><Str>8</Str></Require>
        <Hands>2</Hands>
        <Class>Large</Class>
        <Damage>Slashing</Damage>
        <Bonus>3</Bonus>
    </Weapon>
    
    <Weapon>
        <Name>Mace</Name>
        <Require><Str>6</Str></Require>
        <Hands>1</Hands>
        <Class>Medium</Class>
        <Damage>Crushing</Damage>
        <Bonus>1</Bonus>
    </Weapon>
    
    <Weapon>
        <Name>War Hammer</Name>
        <Require><Str>8</Str></Require>
        <Hands>2</Hands>
        <Class>Large</Class>
        <Damage>Crushing</Damage>
        <Bonus>2</Bonus>
    </Weapon>
    
    <Weapon>
        <Name>Rapier</Name>
        <Require><Dex>8</Dex></Require>
        <Hands>1</Hands>
        <Class>Medium</Class>
        <Damage>Piercing</Damage>
        <Bonus>2</Bonus>
        <Effect>
            <skill add="1">Dodge</skill>
            <skill add="1">Deflect</skill>
            <skill add="1">Counter</skill>
        </Effect>
        <Quick>+1 to Dodge, Deflect and Counter</Quick>
    </Weapon>
    
    <Weapon>
        <Name>Sling</Name>
        <Hands>2</Hands>
        <Class>Small</Class>
        <Damage>Crushing</Damage>
    </Weapon>
    
    <Weapon>
        <Name>Long Bow</Name>
        <Require><Dex>8</Dex></Require>
        <Hands>2</Hands>
        <Class>Ranged</Class>
        <Damage>Piercing</Damage>
        <Bonus>1</Bonus>
        <Range>4</Range>
    </Weapon>

    <Weapon>
        <Name>Short Bow</Name>
        <Require><Dex>8</Dex></Require>
        <Hands>2</Hands>
        <Class>Ranged</Class>
        <Damage>Piercing</Damage>
        <Bonus>3</Bonus>
        <Range>2</Range>
    </Weapon>
    
    <Weapon>
        <Name>Crossbow</Name>
        <Require><Dex>6</Dex></Require>
        <Hands>2</Hands>
        <Class>Ranged</Class>
        <Damage>Piercing</Damage>
        <Bonus>5</Bonus>
    </Weapon>
    
</Skills>