<Skills>
    <Skill>
        <Name>Attack</Name>
        <Stat>Str</Stat>
        <Cost>5</Cost>
        <Synergy>Warrior</Synergy>
        <Text>
            With a powerful swipe of their claws the lycan attacks their victim.
            The skill <name>Attack</name> is an attack of power <check type="str">Attack+1</check>. The damage it deals is equal to its power. Multiple attackers can use <name>Attack</name> to grapple a defender. See Grappled for details.
            The character must either be in Warg Form, Wolf Form or carrying a weapon to use <name>Attack</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Attack</Action>
            <Power type="roll" add="1" weapon="1"><skill>Attack</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Attack for X damage.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Backstab</Name>
        <Require>Attack</Require>
        <Stat>Dex</Stat>
        <Cost>1</Cost>
        <Synergy>Rogue</Synergy>
        <Text>
            Unseen and unheard the skilled rogue can approach a victim and take the time necessary to ensure that the blow they strike is precise and effective.
            A character who is hidden or moving silently can perform a <name>Backstab</name> of power <check type="dex">Attack+Backstab</check>. The attacker gains the +3 bonus for attacking an unaware defender. The damage of this attack is equal to its power.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action type="melee">Attack</Action>
            <Mana>5</Mana>
            <Power type="roll" add="3" weapon="1"><skill>Attack</skill><skill>Backstab</skill></Power>
            <Quick> If unseen, attack for X damage.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>

    <Skill>
        <Name>Ball Lightning</Name>
        <Require>Lightning Bolt</Require>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Spell>Arthur</Spell>
        <Cost>1</Cost>
        <Synergy>Battle Mage</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Arthur</name> the character is able to summon a ball of pure lightning to attack their foes.
            The power of this skill is <check type="fai">Ball Lightning</check>. The character creates a <name>Ball Lightning</name> with level equal to the power of this skill.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>8,2</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Ball Lightning</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Create a Ball Lightning with power X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>

    <Skill>
        <Name>Berserk</Name>
        <Require>Attack</Require>
        <Stat>Str</Stat>
        <Cost>2</Cost>
        <Synergy>Warrior</Synergy>
        <Text>
            Whipping themselves into a fury the character loses track of everything but inflicting pain on those around them.
            The power of this skill is <check type="str">Berserk</check>. The character is <name>Berserk</name> for the result duration and cannot be stopped before this.
            Each turn the character must make a regular attack with the die type increased by two against a target. The character must target a conscious target so long as one exists, conscious friends included. If there are no conscious targets they must target unconscious but alive characters, alive friend included. If there are no unconscious characters they must target an object or dead character.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Mana>10</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Berserk</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Must attack for result level turns.</Quick>
        </Effect>
        <Effect>
            <Action type="melee">Attack</Action>
            <Power type="roll" times="2" weapon="1"><skill>Berserk</skill></Power>
            <Quick>When Berserk attack for X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Black Hole</Name>
        <Require>Portal</Require>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Spell>Oxdoro</Spell>
        <Cost>5</Cost>
        <Synergy>Mechanist</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Oxdoro</name> the character is able to bend space in on itself creating a point in space that sucks everything towards it and crushes those inside.
            The power of this skill is <check type="fai">Black Hole</check>. The duration of this skill is the result duration and the radius of this skill is the result distance. At the start of their turn any character in the radius of this skill, including in the hole, may make a <check type="str">Endurance</check> or <check type="dex">Sprint</check>. If the result of this check is less than the power of this skill then they are sucked to the centre of the hole.
            Any character in the hole may not use their <name>Move Action</name> for that turn. They also take damage equal to the result level of this skill which cannot be defended against.
            Note that if the caster is within the radius then they too can be sucked into the hole.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>10</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Black Hole</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Create a black hole radius X that sucks objects in.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Bless</Name>
        <Name>Curse</Name>
        <Invert/>
        <Divide/>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Spell>Loreanna</Spell>
        <Cost>3</Cost>
        <Synergy>Trickster</Synergy>
        <Text>
            Calling on the power of <name>Loreanna</name> fortune favours someone in all they do.
            The power of the skill is <check type="fai">Bless</check>. The target character gains +2 to all skill checks or -2 to all skill checks in any skill that they have spent <XP/> on. This skill lasts for the result duration. This effect is <name>Divisible</name> and so by reducing the duration the user can give a larger bonus or penalty to skill checks. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>8</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Bless</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Target gets +2 or -2 to all skills.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Blink</Name>
        <Require>Dodge</Require>
        <Stat>Dex</Stat>
        <Spell>Oxdoro</Spell>
        <Cost>3</Cost>
        <Synergy>Mechanist</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Oxdoro</name> the character can quickly bend space so as to travel a short distance without moving.
            If used as a defence the power of this skill is <check type="dex">Dodge+Blink</check>. If the power of the attack is equal to or less than this power then the attack deals no damage nor has any effect on the defender.
            If used as a method of travel the power of this skill is <check type="dex">Blink</check>. In this case the user may move a distance in metres equal to the power of the skill to any visible location. Casting requires a <name>Minor Action</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Defend</Action>
            <Mana>2</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Blink</skill><skill>Dodge</skill></Power>
            <Quick>If X at least attack, then no damage or effect.</Quick>
        </Effect>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Minor</Action>
            <Mana>2</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Blink</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Move a distance of up to X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Block</Name>
        <Require>Attack</Require>
        <Stat>Str</Stat>
        <Cost>4</Cost>
        <Synergy>Warrior</Synergy>
        <Text>
            With a quick response and powerful intent the defender can reduce the impact of any blow.
            Attacks can be defended with a power of <check type="str">Block</check>. Any attack has its power reduced by the power of this skill. If the attack power is reduced to 0 then it also has no effect. If an attack targets multiple characters the attack power is only reduced to this defending character.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Defend</Action>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Block</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Reduce the power of an attack by X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Bloodlust</Name>
        <Require>Attack</Require>
        <Stat>Str</Stat>
        <Cost>2</Cost>
        <Synergy>Warrior</Synergy>
        <Text>
            Sadistically revelling in the misfortune of their target the character gains power as they attack their opponent.
            The power of the attack is <check type="str">Bloodlust</check>. This attack deals damage equal to the power of the attack and gains <HP/> equal to the result level of the attack after defense.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action type="melee">Attack</Action>
            <Mana>2</Mana>
            <Power type="roll" weapon="1"><skill>Bloodlust</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Attack for X. Gain 1 HP for each 2 damage done.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Chain Lightning</Name>
        <Require>Lightning Bolt</Require>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>1</Cost>
        <Spell>Arthur</Spell>
        <Synergy>Battle Mage</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Arthur</name> the caster is able to channel energy to form a massive bolt of lightning that bounces between foes.
            The power of the attack is <check type="fai">Chain Lightning</check>. The caster determines the initial trajectory and can change this trajectory a number of times equal to the result level of the check changing only after hitting a target. Each time the bolt travels in a straight line and hits all characters it crosses. The total distance that the bolt travels is equal to the power of the skill in metres however will stop prior to this if it hits a wall or similarly grounded object.
            The bolt deals damage equal to its power to every creature it passes. Creatures can be hit by the same bolt more than once however they are only targeted by the attack once and so only need to defend once.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action type="ranged">Attack</Action>
            <Mana>10</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Chain Lightning</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Attack for X. May re-target the result level number of times</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>

    <Skill>
        <Name>Channel Mana</Name>
        <Require>Counter-spell</Require>
        <Invert/>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>2</Cost>
        <Spell>Ird'ken</Spell>
        <Synergy>Channeller</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Ird'ken</name> the caster can sap the energies of their foes or provide energy to allies.
            The power of this skill is <check type="fai">Channel Mana</check>. If the target does not resist: the target loses the power in <MP/> and the caster gains the power in <MP/>; or the target gains the power in <MP/> and the caster loses the power in <MP/>. If the target resists then the result level is exchanged instead. A character may not be reduced below <MP>0</MP> by this skill. However they may be raised above <MPMax/>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Minor</Action>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Channel Mana</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Exchange X MP from a target or power level MP if they resist.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>

    <Skill>
        <Name>Charm</Name>
        <Name>Confuse</Name>
        <Require>Fear</Require>
        <Invert/>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>4</Cost>
        <Spell>Ird'ken</Spell>
        <Synergy>Channeller</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Ird'ken</name> the caster can bend the will of their target to their own or simply shatter it.
            When used to charm the power of this skill is <check type="fai">Charm</check>. If twice the power of this skill is greater than the <MP/> of the target then the target is charmed. This means that the target will obey the caster as long as the caster does not require them to go against the principles or motivations of the target. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
            When used to confuse the power of this skill is <check type="fai">Confuse</check>. If twice the power of this skill is greater than the <MP/> of the target then the target becomes confused and aggressive. While in this state the target will not see the difference between friend and foe, attacking the nearest target. If the attack is on a friend then the caster chooses which skill will be used. If the attack is on a foe then the target chooses which skill will be used. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>10,2</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Charm</skill></Power>
            <Quick>If 2X is at least target's MP they are charmed.</Quick>
        </Effect>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>10,2</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Charm</skill></Power>
            <Quick>If 2X is at least target's MP they become confused, attacking characters randomly.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Cleave</Name>
        <Require>Attack</Require>
        <Stat>Str</Stat>
        <Cost>2</Cost>
        <Synergy>Warrior</Synergy>
        <Text>
            With broad powerful strokes the attacker can engage multiple foes at once.
            The power of the attack is <check type="str">Cleave</check>. The skill deals damage equal to its power to at most the result level number of adjacent characters.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action type="melee">Attack</Action>
            <Mana>4</Mana>
            <Power type="roll" weapon="1"><skill>Cleave</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Attack adjacent characters for X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Combo</Name>
        <Require>Attack</Require>
        <Stat>Dex</Stat>
        <Cost>2</Cost>
        <Synergy>Rogue</Synergy>
        <Text>
            While appearing slow at first the attacker gains momentum and blow follows blow at last wreaking massive damage to any foolhardy enough to get in the attacker's way.
            If the attacker's last action was not a successful attack or they choose to restart the <name>Combo</name> the skill's power is <check type="dex">Combo</check>. The attack costs <MP>0</MP> and deals damage equal to its power.
            If the attacker's last action was a successful melee attack then the skill's power is <check type="dex">Combo</check> plus the result of the previous attack after defense. The attack costs <MP>2</MP> plus the cost of the last attack. The attack deals damage equal to its power.
            This means that the power and mana cost of the attack accumulates with successful attacks.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action type="melee">Attack</Action>
            <Mana>0</Mana>
            <Power type="roll" weapon="1"><skill>Combo</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Attack for X costing 0 MP.</Quick>
        </Effect>
        <Effect>
            <Action type="melee">Attack</Action>
            <Mana>X+2</Mana>
            <Power type="roll" weapon="1"><skill>Combo</skill></Power>
            <Quick>If last Major Action was a successful attack then attack for 'X+last result' and costing '2+last MP'.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Control Undead</Name>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>5</Cost>
        <Spell>Innodi</Spell>
        <Synergy>Necromancer</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Innodi</name> a character can bend the minds of creatures with abnormal life to their will.
            The power of the skill is <check type="fai">Control Undead</check>. This power can be split in any way among any number of undead creatures to change whose control they are under. The power required to control a creature not currently controlled is equal to the creature's power. If the creature is currently under control then  twice the creature's power is required. If the creature is currently under control and only the creature's power is reached then the creature is no longer under anyones control. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
            Any controlled undead can be dismissed for <MP>3</MP>. The character gains <HP>1</HP> for each undead dismissed in this way. Dismissing requires a <name>Minor Action</name> however any number of undead can be dismissed at once for <MP>3</MP>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>4</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Control Undead</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Gain control of an undead/golem not under anyones control of level less than X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>4</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Control Undead</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Target undead/golem of level less than X is no longer under anyones control.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Counter</Name>
        <Require>Deflect</Require>
        <Stat>Dex</Stat>
        <Cost>2</Cost>
        <Synergy>Rogue</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By using the attackers own strength against them the defender quickly turns the blow destined for them to the back to attacker themselves.
            The power of the skill is <check type="dex">Counter+1</check>. If this power is equal to or greater than the power of the melee attack then the attack deals no damage nor has any effect. In this case the attacker receives damage equal to the power of this skilll and any effects that the defender would have received. This damage is not considered an attack and so cannot be defended against.
            <name>Counter</name> may be used to defend an adjacent ally.
            This skill cannot be used to defend against projectile attacks.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Defend</Action>
            <Mana>2</Mana>
            <Power type="roll" add="1"><skill>Counter</skill></Power>
            <Quick>If X is at least attack then take no damage and attacker takes X damage.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Counter-spell</Name>
        <Stat>Int</Stat>
        <Cost>2</Cost>
        <Synergy>Channeller</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By interjecting in the target's commune with their deity the character skilfully disrupts the flow of power towards themselves rendering the divine power completely ineffective.
            The power of this skill is <check type="int">Counter-spell</check>. If this power is equal to or greater than the power of a spell just cast targeting the user then all effects of that spell do not occur. A countered spell still requires it's casting cost although no ongoing costs are required. Using this skill requires a <name>Minor Action</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Minor</Action>
            <Mana>5</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Counter-spell</skill></Power>
            <Quick>If X is at least spell power targeting the character then it is cancelled.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Create Golem</Name>
        <Name>Destroy Golem</Name>
        <Require>Raise Undead</Require>
        <Invert/>
        <Divide/>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>2</Cost>
        <Spell>Innodi</Spell>
        <Synergy>Necromancer</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Innodi</name> a character can bring earth and fire to life to fight at their side.
            When creating a golem the power of this skill is <check type="fai">Create Golem</check>. The user can create a <name>Golem</name> of level up to the power of this skill. This effect is <name>Divisible</name> and so level of creature can be sacrificed for quantity of creatures. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name> and a sufficient source of earth or fire dependant on the type of <name>Golem</name>. The casting creates the form so the earth or fire do not have to be shaped by hand.
            For example a character with a check of 9 can create one <name>Golem</name> with level up to 9. They could also create two <name>Golem</name>s with level up to 4 or 3 <name>Golem</name>s with level up to 2.
            This skill costs <MP>1</MP> to sustain for each <name>Golem</name>.
            When destroying a golem the power of this skill is <check type="fai">Destroy Golem</check>. The golem loses power equal to the power of this skill. If the golem falls below <HP>0</HP> or reaches power 0 then it is destroyed.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>8,X</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Create Golem</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Create a golem of power X. Divide power to add a golem. Cost to sustain is equal to number of golems.</Quick>
        </Effect>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Minor</Action>
            <Mana>8</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Destroy Golem</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Remove X power from a summoned Golem.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Devour</Name>
        <Require>Bloodlust</Require>
        <Stat>Str</Stat>
        <Cost>1</Cost>
        <Synergy>Warrior</Synergy>
        <Text>
            Taking advantage of the power of a fallen foe the character consumes their body to restore their own power.
            When used on an incapacitated target the target causes <check type="str">Devour</check> <name>Deep Wounds</name>. For each <name>Deep Wound</name> the target sustains the character gains <HP>1</HP>. Devouring requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action type="melee">Attack</Action>
            <Mana>2</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Devour</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Gain X HP and deal X deep wound to incapacitated foe.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Deflect</Name>
        <Require>Dodge</Require>
        <Stat>Dex</Stat>
        <Cost>2</Cost>
        <Synergy>Rogue</Synergy>
        <Text>
            Spotting weakness in a character's attack the defender swiftly parries and opens the attacker for a quick riposte.
            The power of the defence is <check type="dex">Deflect+1</check>. If this power is equal to or greater than the power of the melee attack then it deals no damage nor has any effect and the attacker is <name>Stun</name>ned for 1 turn. Note that <name>Tough Fighter</name> does not affect this skill.
            <name>Deflect</name> may be used to defend an adjacent ally.
            This skill cannot be used to defend against projectile attacks.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Defend</Action>
            <Mana>2</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Deflect</skill></Power>
            <Quick>If X is at least attack power then take no damage and attacker is stunned for 1 turn.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Divine Arrow</Name>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>4</Cost>
        <Spell>Arthur</Spell>
        <Synergy>Battle Mage</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of Arthur the caster summons an arrow from the ether and fires it at its hapless victim.
            The power of the attack is <check type="fai">Divine Arrow</check>. It deals damage equal to it's power.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action type="ranged">Attack</Action>
            <Mana>3</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Divine Arrow</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Attack for X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Divine Contract</Name>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>1</Cost>
        <Spell>Ird'ken</Spell>
        <Synergy>Channeller</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Ird'ken</name> the caster binds their will into the fate of their target.
            The power of this skill is equal to its level. A willing target must complete a goal specified by the caster. If they fail this goal they immediately receive <check type="fai">power<times/>5</check> <name>Deep Wound</name>s to a maximum of the target's <HPMax/>.
            While this skill is a spell it is unaffected by <name>Counter-spell</name>, <name>Spell Shield</name>, <name>Inversion</name> and <name>Steal Spell</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>20</Mana>
            <Power type="roll" times="5"><skill>Divine Contract</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Willing target must obey contract. If they fail to roll for X and they take X deep wounds.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Dodge</Name>
        <Stat>Dex</Stat>
        <Cost>3</Cost>
        <Synergy>Rogue</Synergy>
        <Text>
            With a swift and quick step the defender avoids even the most massive attack.
            The power of this skill is <check type="dex">Dodge+1</check>. If this power is equal to or greater than the attack power the it deals no damage nor has any effect on the defender.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Defend</Action>
            <Power type="roll" add="1"><skill>Dodge</skill></Power>
            <Quick>If X is at least attack power then take no damage.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Endurance</Name>
        <Stat>Str</Stat>
        <Cost>1</Cost>
        <Text>
            This character is strong and has learnt to endure even the harshest conditions.
            The character can attempt a dead lift of any object with power equal to <check type="str">Endurance</check>. If the weight of the object is at most three times the result weight then it can be lifted.
            Unskilled <Str/> actions can be performed with a power of <check type="str">Endurance+1</check>. Any skill with an <Str/> icon requires this skill.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Endurance</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Lift objects up to three times the result weight.</Quick>
        </Effect>
        <Effect>
            <Power type="roll" add="1"><skill>Endurance</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Unskilled Str action with power X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Extra HP</Name>
        <Cost>5</Cost>
        <Synergy>Warrior</Synergy>
        <Text>
            The character is healthy beyond normal bounds.
            Each level of this skill increases the character's maximum <HP/> by three. As death occurs at -<HPMax/> this skill increases the range that a character will remain unconscious but not dead.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Power times="3"><skill>Extra HP</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Character gains +X to max HP.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Extra MP</Name>
        <Cost>5</Cost>
        <Synergy>Lore</Synergy>
        <Text>
            This character has willpower beyond normal bounds. Each level of this skill increases the character's maximum <MP/> by three.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Power times="3"><skill>Extra MP</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Character gains +X to max MP</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Fear</Name>
        <Name>Anger</Name>
        <Invert/>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>4</Cost>
        <Spell>Ird'ken</Spell>
        <Synergy>Channeller</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Ird'ken</name> the caster can instill fear into a single target or make a character unquestionably the target of attack.
            When used to cause fear this skill has power <check type="fai">Fear</check>. If twice the power of the skill is greater than the <MP/> of the target then the target becomes afraid of the caster and may not attack them under any circumstances and will try to avoid them as much a possible. If the power of the skill is greater than twice the <MP/> of the target then the target will attempt to flee. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
            When used to anger this skill has power <check type="fai">Anger</check>. To use this skill a single character is chosen and the skill targets all characters who are opposed to the chosen character. All targeted characters with <MP/> less than twice the power of this skill must attack the chosen character. The attackers may use any attack skill they wish and if it is impossible for them to attack the target they may take whatever action they wish. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>5,1</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Fear</skill></Power>
            <Quick>If 2X is at least targets MP then target fears the caster.</Quick>
        </Effect>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>5,1</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Fear</skill></Power>
            <Quick>If 2X is at least targets MP then target attacks a scapegoat.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Fireball</Name>
        <Require>Divine Arrow</Require>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>2</Cost>
        <Spell>Arthur</Spell>
        <Synergy>Battle Mage</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Arthur</name> the caster is able to channel energy to form a ball of fire which is then hurled at its hapless victims exploding on contact.
            The power of this skill is <check type="fai">Fireball</check>. This skill deals damage equal to its power and has radius equal to half its result distance. A character that receives at least 5 damage from this skill is <name>On Fire</name> with power equal to the power of this skill.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action type="ranged">Attack</Action>
            <Mana>8</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Fireball</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Attack anyone in radius of half result distance for X. If X is at least 5 then on fire for X as well.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>

    <Skill>
        <Name>Flight</Name>
        <Require>Telekinesis</Require>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>1</Cost>
        <Spell>Oxdoro</Spell>
        <Synergy>Mechanist</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Oxdoro</name> the caster is able to defy gravity.
            The power of this skill is <check type="fai">Flight</check>. Instead of a regular <name>Move Action</name> the target may move the result distance in any direction. This movement is affected by wind.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>3,1</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Flight</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Fly instead of move up to result distance.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Focus</Name>
        <Cost>3</Cost>
        <Synergy>Rogue</Synergy>
        <Text>
            While the physical limits of the character have not changed through force of willpower a character maintains consciousness while badly injured.
            For each level in this skill the range in which a character remains conscious is increased by 3. A character will die by falling below -<HPMax/> regardless of this skill. Regain consciousness rolls are unaffected by this skill. A character with this skill still needs to return to positive health and make a regular regain conscoiusness roll once unconscious.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Power times="3"><skill>Focus</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Stay conscious until -X HP</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Fog</Name>
        <Name>Wind</Name>
        <Invert/>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>2</Cost>
        <Spell>Innodi</Spell>
        <Synergy>Necromancer</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Innodi</name> the caster can summon a great fog concealing all or a great wind.
            If attempting to create a fog the power of the skill is <check type="fai">Fog</check>. The radius of the fog is the skills power in metres. Any character attempting to move more than one meter in a turn must make a <check type="dex">Sprint</check> roll greater than the power of the fog or fall over. Ranged non-area effect attacks cannot be made and mêlée attacks are reduced by the power of the fog. Every character in the fog gains the power of the skill in <name>Stealth</name>. The fog takes one turn to dissipate. It costs no mana for this turn but has full effect during that turn.
            If attempting to create a great wind the power of the skill is <check type="fai">Fog</check>. The radius of the wind is equal to its power. Any character in the blast must make a <check type="dex">Sprint</check> check and if this roll is less than the power of the wind they will fall over after travelling a distance in metres equal to the check. Any type of fog in the area of the blast will have its power reduced by the power of the wind to a minimum of zero at which the fog has completely dissipated.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>5,1</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Fog</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Create a fog of strength X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>5,1</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Wind</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Create a wind of strength X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Haste</Name>
        <Name>Slow</Name>
        <Invert/>
        <Divide/>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>5</Cost>
        <Spell>Oxdoro</Spell>
        <Synergy>Mechanist</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Oxdoro</name> the caster can create a pocket of space containing a single character where the flow of time is altered.
            The power of this skill is <check type="fai">Haste</check>. The target gains +1 or -1 to <name>Speed</name> for the result duration. This effect is <name>Divisible</name> and so the duration may be halved to add an additional +1 or -1 to speed. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>10</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Haste</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Target character gains +1 or -1 to their speed. Divide to add an additional +1 or -1.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Heal</Name>
        <Name>Hurt</Name>
        <Invert/>
        <Divide/>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>5</Cost>
        <Spell>Innodi</Spell>
        <Synergy>Necromancer</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Innodi</name> the caster can directly heal the life force or drain the life force from a creature.
            The power of the skill is <check type="fai">Heal</check>. This skill can increase or reduce the <HP/> of a character by the power of the skill in <HP/>. This skill is not an attack skill and hence when it is used to reduce a characters <HP/> the target cannot use a defence skill. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>. Note that this skill can raise a character's <HP/> above <HPMax/>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>5</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Heal</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Target gains or loses X HP.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Heal Deep Wounds</Name>
        <Name>Cause Deep Wounds</Name>
        <Require>Heal</Require>
        <Invert/>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>5</Cost>
        <Spell>Innodi</Spell>
        <Synergy>Necromancer</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Innodi</name> the caster can heal even the most dire of wounds, or cause them.
            The power of this skill is <check type="fai">Heal Deep Wounds</check>. This skill can reduce the number of <name>Deep Wounds</name> by its result level or alternatively can cause cause a number of <name>Deep Wounds</name> equal to its result level . If used to heal <name>Deep Wounds</name> and the power of this skill is greater than the number <name>Deep Wounds</name> then the remaining power is used to heal regular wounds. The casting time is around one minute.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>10</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Heal Deep Wounds</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Target gains or loses result level deep wounds</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Hold Person</Name>
        <Name>Free Person</Name>
        <Invert/>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>5</Cost>
        <Spell>Oxdoro</Spell>
        <Synergy>Mechanist</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Oxdoro</name> the caster can magically bind creature in one spot.
            The power of this skill is <check type="fai">Hold Person</check>. This power lasts for the result duration. The target can no longer move and so on their turn cannot move, take a <name>Major Action</name> nor any action that requires movement. They still get a <name>Minor Action</name> however they may not use it to perform any physical action apart from speaking or casting spells. This skill requires a <name>Major Action</name> to cast and then a <name>Major Action</name> each following turn to sustain it.
            Alternatively any target character now has a normal movement phase and <name>Major Action</name> whether or not another skill restricts them. This does not provide any effect on an unconscious character however does grant a <name>Major Action</name> to someone under the effects of a <name>Slow</name> spell. This skill requires a <name>Major Action</name> to sustain it.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>8,2</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Hold Person</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Target has no Major Action, or if they have no Major Action they now have one.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Inferno</Name>
        <Require>Fireball</Require>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>1</Cost>
        <Spell>Arthur</Spell>
        <Synergy>Battle Mage</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Arthur</name> the character creates an explosion of flame emanating from the character in all directions.
            The power of this skill is <check type="fai">Inferno</check>. The radius of this effect is equal to the power of this skill in metres, excluding the caster, and the damage is equal to its power. Anyone who takes damage from this skill is <name>On Fire</name> with power equal to the power of this skill. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action type="ranged">Attack</Action>
            <Mana>10</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Inferno</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Attack everyone in a radius of X for X and they are on fire for X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Impenetrable Field</Name>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>3</Cost>
        <Spell>Arthur</Spell>
        <Synergy>Battle Mage</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Arthur</name> the caster creates a barrier that protects them from any harm.
            The power of this skill is <check type="fai">Impenetrable Field</check>. The field has <HP/> equal to the power of the skill. The field has the skill <name>Block</name> at the level of half the power of this skill. When any attacker targets the character they target the field instead. When the field drops to <HP>0</HP> it is destroyed and any remaining damage targets the character instead. During the Refresh and Regenerate phase of Combat the field loses <HP>1</HP>. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>5</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Impenetrable Field</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Gain a field with HP of X and Block at level X/2</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Increase Size</Name>
        <Name>Reduce Size</Name>
        <Invert/>
        <Divide/>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>4</Cost>
        <Spell>Oxdoro</Spell>
        <Synergy>Mechanist</Synergy>
        <Text>
            Calling on the power of <name>Oxdoro</name> the character can warp the size of any creature or object.
            The power of the skill is <check type="fai">Alter Size</check>. The target either gains a size class or loses a size class, decided by the user. The duration of the skill is equal to the result duration. This effect is <name>Divisible</name> so by sacrificing duration the character can add or subtract an additional size class. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
            For rules on size classes and effects see <name>Altered Size</name> for details.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>7</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Increase Size</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Target gains or loses a size class. Divide to add or lose an additional class.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Increase Stat</Name>
        <Name>Reduce Stat</Name>
        <Divide/>
        <Invert/>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>5</Cost>
        <Spell>Loreanna</Spell>
        <Synergy>Trickster</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Loreanna</name> a character suddenly becomes more powerful in a specific way.
            The power of this skill is <check type="fai">Change Stat</check>. The caster chooses either <Str/>, <Dex/>, <Int/> or <Fai/> and the target gains an extra die level or loses a die level to that stat for a duration equal to the result duration. This effect is <name>Divisible</name> so by reducing the duration the caster can increase the number of dice levels gained or lost. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>7</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Increase Stat</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Target gains +1 or -1 to either Str, Dex, Int or Fai. Divide for an additional +1 or -1.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Increase Stats</Name>
        <Name>Reduce Stats</Name>
        <Require>Increase Stat</Require>
        <Invert/>
        <Divide/>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>3</Cost>
        <Spell>Loreanna</Spell>
        <Synergy>Trickster</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of Loreanna a character suddenly becomes more powerful in every way.
            The power of this skill is <check type="fai">Change Stats</check>. The target gains an extra die level or loses a die level to all of <Str/>, <Dex/>, <Int/> and <Fai/> for a duration equal to the result duration. This effect is <name>Divisible</name> so by reducing the duration the caster can increase the number of dice levels gained or lost. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>10</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Increase Stats</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Target gains +1 or -1 to all of Str, Dex, Int and Fai. Divide for an additional +1 or -1.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Initiative</Name>
        <Stat>Int</Stat>
        <Cost>2</Cost>
        <Synergy>Rogue</Synergy>
        <Text>
            Ever ready for action the character anticipates the actions of others.
            This skill is used at the start of combat. The power is <check type="int">Initiative+1</check>. The turn order of characters is determined by the highest power of this skill. If there is a tie then then the characters that tied reroll to see who goes first amongst themselves.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Power type="roll" add="1"><skill>Initiative</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Roll for X at start of combat. Turn order is descending X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Inversion</Name>
        <Require>Counter-spell</Require>
        <Stat>Int</Stat>
        <Cost>3</Cost>
        <Synergy>Channeller</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By carefully disrupting the communication between a caster and their deity they can, in some way, reverse the effect of a spell.
            The power of this skill is <check type="int">Inversion</check>. If the power of this skill is equal to or greater than the power of a spell just cast targeting the user then the spell targets the caster instead or a spell that is invertible uses the inverse ability but not both. The caster still pays the casting cost but the character may, if they choose to, pay the ongoing costs to increase its duration in the same way that the original caster could. Casting requires a <name>Minor Action</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Minor</Action>
            <Mana>7</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Inversion</skill></Power>
            <Quick>If X is at least the power of a spell then either its effect is inverted or it targets the caster instead.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Invisibility</Name>
        <Name>Locate</Name>
        <Require>Light</Require>
        <Invert/>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>1</Cost>
        <Spell>Loreanna</Spell>
        <Synergy>Trickster</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Loreanna</name> the caster can either detect the presence of an object or conceal it from view.
            If trying to conceal a character or object the power is <check type="fai">Invisibility</check>. If it is an object it reduces the power of any <name>Observation</name> check targeting the object by the power of this skill. Note that this skill does not affect <name>Sense</name> checks. If a character is targeted they gain the power of this skill to their <name>Stealth</name> skill regardless of whether they have spent points in that skill or not. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
            If trying to find a character or object the power of this skill is <check type="fai">Locate</check>. The surrounds of an object are known at a radius equal to the power of this skill in metres. If the character is within this radius they know the exact location of the object otherwise they only know the direction of the object. Casting requires a <name>Minor Action</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Minor</Action>
            <Mana>5,1</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Invisibility</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Target gains +X to the result of any stealth rolls</Quick>
        </Effect>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Minor</Action>
            <Mana>5</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Locate</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Find an object within a radius of result distance.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Light</Name>
        <Name>Darkness</Name>
        <Invert/>
        <Divide/>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>3</Cost>
        <Spell>Loreanna</Spell>
        <Synergy>Trickster</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Loreanna</name> the caster can channel light either shinning with divine light or sucking the light out of the environment.
            This skill can, without a check or <MP/> cost, produce sufficient light to see by under any non-divine conditions. Casting requires a <name>Minor Action</name>.
            The power of this skill <check type="fai">Light</check>. The caster can increase or reduce the light in the current location by one for a duration equal to the power of this skill in turns. See <name>Environmental Light</name> for details. This effect is <name>Divisible</name> so by reducing the duration the caster can increase or decrease the light further. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Minor</Action>
            <Mana>2</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Light</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Increase or reduce light level by one. Divide to add or reduce by a further one.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Lightning Bolt</Name>
        <Require>Divine Arrow</Require>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>3</Cost>
        <Spell>Arthur</Spell>
        <Synergy>Battle Mage</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Arthur</name> the caster is able to channel energy to form a massive bolt of lightning to strike their foes.
            The power of the skill is <check type="fai">Lightning Bolt</check>. The path of the bolt is a line starting at the character and will continue for the power of the skill in metres or until it hits a wall or similarly grounded object. Every character in this path takes damage equal to the power of this skill.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action type="ranged">Attack</Action>
            <Mana>8</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Lightning Bolt</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Attack for X everyone in a line of length X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Locks and Traps</Name>
        <Stat>Dex</Stat>
        <Cost>3</Cost>
        <Synergy>Rogue</Synergy>
        <Text>
            The character is especially skilled at mechanisms. This provides them the ability to manipulate mechanical locks and traps as well as the experience necessary to observe the location of traps.
            If the character is attempting to pick a mechanical lock the power of this skill is <check type="dex">Locks and Traps</check>. If the power of the skill is greater than or equal to the power of a lock then it is unlocked. Only one attempt to pick a lock is permitted and it requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
            If the character is attempting to force a mechanical lock the power of this skill is <check type="str">Locks and Traps+2</check>. If the power of the skill is greater than or equal to the power of a lock then it is unlocked. If the power of the skill is less than the power of the lock then the lock is broken. A broken lock cannot be picked nor forced nor unlocked with the correct key. Forcing a lock requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
            When the <name>Observation</name> skill is used to search for traps the power of the skill becomes <check type="int">Observation+Locks and Traps</check>.
            If the character is attempting to disarm or set a trap the power of this skill is <check type="dex">Locks and Traps</check>. A sufficiently bad power when attempting to disarm a trap will set it off. To set a trap the right tools are needed and the power of the trap is equal to the power of this skill. Typically setting a trap takes around ten minutes.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>2</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Locks and Traps</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Unlock a lock of strength up to X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Power type="roll" stat="Str" add="2"><skill>Locks and Traps</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Force a lock of strength up to X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>2</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Locks and Traps</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Arm or disarm a trap of strength up to X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Lore</Name>
        <Stat>Int</Stat>
        <Cost>2</Cost>
        <Synergy>Lore</Synergy>
        <Text>
            A character with this skill is particularly knowledgable when it comes to divine lore.
            The character can attempt to remember knowledge with a cheock of power <check type="int">Lore</check>. Having access to a library or similar source will provide bonuses to this check.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Power type="roll" add="1"><skill>Lore</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Know about lore with power X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Lunge</Name>
        <Stat>Str</Stat>
        <Cost>3</Cost>
        <Synergy>Warrior</Synergy>
        <Text>
            With great power the character near instantly closes the distance to a foe landing on them with a crushing blow.
            A character starts a lunge in the same way they jump using the <name>Sprint</name> skill except they use this skill for the roll. They may end the leap with an attack. If so they may make a basic <name>Attack</name> roll and add the <name>Lunge</name> roll to the damage. They may not add more damage than is one result distance further than they jumped. For example if a character lunges 5m then one result distance further is the result range 6-10 and so the added damage cannot be more than 10.
            A character who chooses a to <name>Lunge</name> may move as though they spent their <name>Major Action</name> as a <name>Move Action</name>. A character may not <name>Lunge</name> by first moving away from a target and then towards.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action type="melee">Attack</Action>
            <Mana>2</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Lunge</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Lunge at someone gaining Lunge plus a standard attack to anyone within the result distance.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Observation</Name>
        <Stat>Int</Stat>
        <Cost>1</Cost>
        <Text>
            This character has honed their ability to see or hear even the smallest of details.
            The character can actively or passively noticing something visual or aural with a power of <check type="int">Observation+1</check>.
            They can perform unskilled <Int/> actions can be performed with a power of <check type="int">Observation+1</check>. Any skill with an <Int/> icon requires this skill.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Observation</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Observe with a power of X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
        <Effect>
            <Power type="roll" add="1"><skill>Observation</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Unskilled Int action with power X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Permanence</Name>
        <Require>Phase Shift</Require>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>3</Cost>
        <Spell>Oxdoro</Spell>
        <Synergy>Mechanist</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling the power of <name>Oxdoro</name> the character can take temporary energies and make them permanent.
            The power of this skill is <check type="fai">Permanence</check>. If the power of this skill is at least the power of a spell with ongoing mana costs the spell no longer requires the ongoing cost. However the caster of the ongoing spell reduces their <MPMax/> by twice the ongoing cost. If the skill required a <name>Major Action</name> to sustain it now requires a <name>Minor Action</name>. If the skill required a <name>Minor Action</name> to sustain it now requires no action to sustain.
        </Text>t
        <Effect>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Permanence</skill></Power>
            <Mana>5</Mana>
            <Quick>If X is at least the power of a spell, the caster gets -2X to max MP but pays no more MP.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Phase Shift</Name>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>2</Cost>
        <Spell>Oxdoro</Spell>
        <Synergy>Mechanist</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling the power of <name>Oxdoro</name> the character can slide slightly outside the realm of existence.
            The power of this skill is <check type="fai">Phase Shift</check>. The user can becomes <name>Ethereal</name> for the result duration. Casting requires a <name>Minor Action</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Phase Shift</skill></Power>
            <Mana>5,2</Mana>
            <Quick>Become Ethereal.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Poison</Name>
        <Name>Cure Poison</Name>
        <Invert/>
        <Stat>Int</Stat>
        <Cost>3</Cost>
        <Synergy>Rogue</Synergy>
        <Text>
            The character has an intimate knowledge of poisons and their cures.
            When a character makes a successful standard Attack the defender is poisoned with power <check type="int">Poison</check>. If the character is using a piercing weapon then they have a bonus of +2 to their <name>Poison</name> roll.
            Alternatively a character may use a <name>Major Action</name> to cure a poison with power of <check type="int">Poison</check>. If the character is currently under the effects of a poison then the poison is reduced in power by the power of this skill. If a character is not under the effects of a poison but was poisoned within the last hour then the character can counteract the long term effects of a poison. For example the <name>Deep Wounds</name> caused by a poison.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Mana>2</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Poison</skill></Power>
            <Quick>After a successful attack target is poisoned for X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>2</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Cure Poison</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Reduce the strength of a poison by X or heal X deep wounds made by poison.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Poison Cloud</Name>
        <Require>Fog</Require>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>3</Cost>
        <Spell>Innodi</Spell>
        <Synergy>Necromancer</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Innodi</name> the character can summon a poisonous cloud that saps the energy from any creature caught inside.
            The power of this skill is <check type="fai">Poison Cloud</check>. The radius of the cloud is the result distance. A <name>Poison Cloud</name> has all the properties of <name>Fog</name>. Any turn that a character ends while in the cloud must make a <check type="str">Endurance</check> or <check type="fai">Sense</check> check. If a character fails this check they are effected by <name>Poison</name> with a power equal to the power of the cloud.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>8,2</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Poison Cloud</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Create a cloud with strength X that poisons for X to anyone caught inside.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Poison Dart</Name>
        <Require>Divine Arrow</Require>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>2</Cost>
        <Spell>Innodi</Spell>
        <Synergy>Necromancer</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Innodi</name> the character summons an ethereal dart laced with poison.
            The power of this attack is <check type="fai">Poison Dart</check>. The target becomes <name>Poisoned</name> with power equal to the power of this attack.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action type="ranged">Attack</Action>
            <Mana>5</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Poison Dart</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Attack for X. If successful it poisons for X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Portal</Name>
        <Require>Telekinesis</Require>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>3</Cost>
        <Spell>Oxdoro</Spell>
        <Synergy>Mechanist</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Oxdoro</name> the character is able to link disparate places in space to allow thoroughfare between them.
            When used to create a first portal this skill always succeeds and required a <name>Minor Action</name>.
            When used to create a portal that links to another portal the power of this skill is <check type="fai">Portal</check>. If the portal to be created is no further than two to the power of this skill in metres to an existing portal then the creation succeeds and the portals are linked as well as any other portals currently linked to the existing portal. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
            Any character may move into any portal and exit at any of its linked portals. The ongoing <MP/> cost of this skill is equal to the number of linked portals beyond the first. The character may at any time choose to close all the portals or for a <name>Minor Action</name> close a particular portal. Closing a portal does not affect the linked nature of any remaining portals no matter how they were originally created and linked. Portals cannot close while objects are passing through them. 
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>2</Mana>
            <Power>-</Power>
            <Quick>Create the first portal.</Quick>
        </Effect>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>5,X</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Portal</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Create a portal and link to an existing portal within 2 to the X metres. Ongoing cost is one less than the number of portals.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Precision Attack</Name>
        <Require>Attack</Require>
        <Stat>Dex</Stat>
        <Cost>2</Cost>
        <Synergy>Rogue</Synergy>
        <Text>
            The character has excellent knowledge of all creatures weak points and the training to strike at them.
            The power of this attack is <check type="dex" penalty="1">Attack+Precision Attack</check>. The damage is equal to the power of the attack. They may use a <name>Minor Action</name> to get an additional +1 to their skill check.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Attack</Action>
            <Mana>1</Mana>
            <Power type="roll" die="-1" weapon="1"><skill>Precision Attack</skill><skill>Attack</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Attack for X. Spend a Minor Action to get +1.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Raise Undead</Name>
        <Name>Hurt Undead</Name>
        <Require>Control Undead</Require>
        <Invert/>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>3</Cost>
        <Spell>Innodi</Spell>
        <Synergy>Necromancer</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Innodi</name> the character gives life to those who are recently departed.
            The power of this skill is <check type="fai">Raise Undead</check>. The caster can raise up to the power of this skill in levels of creatures who have recently died to create <name>Undead</name> warriors. No matter how many undead are raised the ongoing cost is always <MP>1</MP>.
            Any controlled undead can be dismissed for <MP>3</MP>. The caster gains <HP>1</HP> for each undead dismissed in this way.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>5,1</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Raise Undead</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Raise an undead with power X. Divide to raise an additional undead.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Random Fate</Name>
        <Require>Bless</Require>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>1</Cost>
        <Spell>Loreanna</Spell>
        <Synergy>Trickster</Synergy>
        <Text>
            The caster puts the fate of a character in the hands of <name>Loreanna</name>
            The power of the attack is <check type="fai">Chaos Bolt</check>. The fate of the character is given to <name>Loreanna</name> who decides their fate dependant on the result level of this skill after defense is calculated.
            0: +1 to all skills for 1 turn.
            1: Nothing happens.
            2: Knocked Prone.
            3: -1 die type to all skills for 2 turns.
            4: -1 to Speed for 6 turns.
            5: Stunned for 5 turns.
            6: The target dies.
            7: The caster decides their fate.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action type="ranged">Attack</Action>
            <Mana>5</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Chaos Bolt</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Randomly determine a character's fate.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Redirect</Name>
        <Require>Divine Arrow</Require>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>1</Cost>
        <Spell>Arthur</Spell>
        <Synergy>Battle Mage</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Arthur</name> the character is able to take a projectile and fire it back to its origin.
            The power of this skill is <check type="fai">Redirect</check>. If the power of the projectile attack is equal to or less than this power then the attack targets the attacker instead.
            This skill may be used to redirect a projectile targeting another character. The effect is the same however a <name>Minor Action</name> is required if used in this way.
            This skill may only be used on projectile attacks.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Defend</Action>
            <Mana>4</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Redirect</skill></Power>
            <Quick>If X is at least a projectile attack then the attack targets the attacker.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Refresh</Name>
        <Cost>5</Cost>
        <Synergy>Lore</Synergy>
        <Text>
            The character has great propensity to renew mental energies.
            The character's refresh rate is equal to the level of this skill minus 5.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Power add="-10" times="0.5"><skill>Refresh</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Target gains MP at a rate of X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Regenerate</Name>
        <Cost>5</Cost>
        <Synergy>Warrior</Synergy>
        <Text>
            The character has great propensity to renew physical health.
            The character's regenerate rate is equal to half the level of this skill minus 5.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Power add="-10" times="0.5"><skill>Regenerate</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Target gains HP at a rate of X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Sense</Name>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>1</Cost>
        <Text>
            This character has honed their ability to sense to even minor changes in the world around them.
            Actively or passively noticing something non-visual and non-aural with power <check type="fai">Sense+1</check>.
            Unskilled <Fai/> actions can be performed with a power of <check type="fai">Sense+1</check>. Any skill with a <Fai/> icon requires this skill.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Power type="roll" add="1"><skill>Sense</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Sense with a power of X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
        <Effect>
            <Power type="roll" add="1"><skill>Sense</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Unskilled Fai action with power X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Sleep</Name>
        <Name>Wake</Name>
        <Require>Fear</Require>
        <Invert/>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>2</Cost>
        <Spell>Ird'ken</Spell>
        <Synergy>Channeller</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Ird'ken</name> the caster can gain control over their state of consciousness.
            If trying to cause a character to sleep the power of this skill is <check type="fai">Sleep</check>. The duration of this skill is equal ot its power in turns. While under the influence of this skill the targeted character has their <HP/> lowered by power of this skill for the purposes of consciousness and unconsciousness. Note that this does not affect at what <HP/> a character dies, only when they fall unconscious or regain consciousness. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
            If trying to wake an unconscious character the power is <check type="fai">Wake</check>. For the duration of this skill the character has their <HP/> raised by the power of this skill for the purposes of consciousness and unconsciousness. Note this does not affect at what <HP/> a character dies, only when they fall unconscious or regain consciousness. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
            An unaware target who remains conscious may make a <check>Notice</check> to see if they notice the effect. If the notice power is at least the power of the skill then they notice.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>5,1</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Sleep</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Target gains or loses X to their HP for the purposes of consciousness</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Spell Shield</Name>
        <Require>Counter-spell</Require>
        <Stat>Int</Stat>
        <Cost>2</Cost>
        <Synergy>Channeller</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By interjecting in the target's commune with their deity the character skilfully disrupts the flow of power rendering the divine power completely ineffective.
            The power of this skill is <check type="int">Spell Shield</check>. If the power of this skill is equal to or greater than the power of any spell just cast then all the effects of that spell do not occur. A countered spell stills requires it's casting cost although no ongoing costs are required. Casting requires a <name>Minor Action</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>7</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Spell Shield</skill></Power>
            <Quick>If X is at least the power of a spell it is countered.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Sprint</Name>
        <Stat>Dex</Stat>
        <Cost>1</Cost>
        <Text>
            This character is particularly agile and can move with grace and speed.
            In combat the character can move a number of metres each turn dependant on the result level of the level of the skill. Note that armour can affect movement speed. Outside of combat the character can move the same distance but each second.
            A character may use movement speed to jump horizontally. If so they make a <check type="dex">Sprint</check> and the result distance is the maximum number of metres they can jump. A run up will help a character to jump. A character may not jump more than two metres further than their run up.
            A character may use movement speed to jump vertically. If so they make a <check type="dex">Sprint</check> and the result distance halved indicates the maximum number of metres they can jump. A run up does not help a character jump vertically.
            Unskilled <Dex/> actions can be performed with a power of <check type="dex">Sprint+1</check>. Any skill with an <Dex/> icon requires this skill.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Sprint</skill></Power>
            <Quick>The character can jump the result distance horizontally or half that vertically.</Quick>
        </Effect>
        <Effect>
            <Power type="roll" add="1"><skill>Sprint</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Unskilled Dex action with power X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Stealth</Name>
        <Stat>Dex</Stat>
        <Cost>2</Cost>
        <Synergy>Rogue</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By staying in the shadows and sensing others movements around them the character can remain unseen.
            If hiding the power of this skill is <check type="dex">Stealth+2</check>. As long as this power is larger then a passive <name>Observation</name> check by those around them they remain hidden. For the duration that the user remains hidden only one roll is made. Hiding requires a <name>Minor Action</name>.
            If stealthily moving the power of this skill is <check type="dex">Stealth+1</check>. As long as this power is larger then a passive <name>Observation</name> check by those around them they remain hidden. For the duration that the user remains hidden only one roll is made. While moving this skill costs <MP>1</MP> to sustain. A character may stop moving to avoid paying this cost. Stealthy movement requries a <name>Minor Action</name>.
            If picking someone's pocket this skill has power of <check type="dex">Stealth</check>. If this is greater than a passive <name>Observation</name> check by the target then the item is stolen. This action costs <MP>5</MP> and requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>1</Mana>
            <Power type="roll" add="2"><skill>Stealth</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Hide with power X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>1,1</Mana>
            <Power type="roll" add="1"><skill>Stealth</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Move stealthily with power X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>5</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Stealth</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Pick pocket with power X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Steal Spell</Name>
        <Require>Inversion</Require>
        <Stat>Int</Stat>
        <Cost>1</Cost>
        <Synergy>Channeller</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By incredible skill the character interjects into a caster's commune with their deity they gain complete control of the spell, wielding it in any way they choose.
            The power of this skill is <check type="int">Steal Spell</check>. If this is greater than or equal to the power of a spell that has just been cast then the spell targets whoever the character wishes, if invertible they may invert the spell and if <name>Divisible</name> they may divide it. The power of the spell becomes the power of this skill. The casting cost is paid by the caster but the user may pay the ongoing costs to increase its duration in the same way that the original caster could. This skill requires a <name>Minor Action</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Minor</Action>
            <Mana>10</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Steal Spell</skill></Power>
            <Quick>If X is at least the power of a spell it becomes power X cast by this character.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Stun Attack</Name>
        <Require>Attack</Require>
        <Stat>Str</Stat>
        <Cost>2</Cost>
        <Synergy>Rogue</Synergy>
        <Text>
            The character moves with quick strikes that, while doing no damage, confounds the target and stuns them for a short period.
            This attack has a power of <check type="str">Stun Attack</check>. The power of this attack is reduced by the defence skill used regardless of which defence skill is used. The defender is stunned for a number of turns equal to the remaining result level.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action type="melee">Attack</Action>
            <Mana>3</Mana>
            <Power type="roll" weapon="1"><skill>Stun Attack</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Attack for X. All defence skills reduce X. Stun for result level turns.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Stunning Bolt</Name>
        <Require>Divine Arrow</Require>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>4</Cost>
        <Spell>Loreanna</Spell>
        <Synergy>Trickster</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Loreanna</name> the character is able to summon a divine bolt which confounds whomever it strikes.
            The power of this attack is <check type="fai">Stunning Bolt</check>. The power of this attack is reduced by the defence skill regardless of which skill is used. The target is <name>Stun</name>ned for a number of turns equal to the remaining result level.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action type="ranged">Attack</Action>
            <Mana>6</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Stunning Bolt</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Attack for X. All defence skills reduce X. Stun for result level turns.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>

    <Skill>
        <Name>Swarm of Rats</Name>
        <Require>Raise Undead</Require>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>1</Cost>
        <Spell>Innodi</Spell>
        <Synergy>Necromancer</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Innodi</name> the character is able to call on small creatures to attack their foes.
            The power of this skill is <check type="fai">Swarm of Rats</check>. The first turn nothing happens. Before the characters next turn a number of rats is summoned equal to the result level of this skill. Each rat has <HP>1</HP> and attacks for 2 slashing damage each turn. This damage ignores shields. This skill costs <MP>1</MP> to sustain for each result level of rats remaining, including the first turn. For example: if there are 7 rats left the skill costs <MP>3</MP>. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
            The entire swarm is controlled with a single simple command such as to attack a particular character or to congregate in a particular area. If the sustain cost is not paid then the results are unpredictable. Most animals will disperse but some may attack random targets.
            In urban environments rats are exclusively summoned. In other environments many other small species may instead appear. Such as other small mammals, lizards, snakes or even small birds. Their stats remain the same no matter what small animals are summoned.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>5,X</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Swarm of Rats</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Summon X rats. Each rat has <HP>1</HP> and attacks for 2 damages ignoring shields.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Switch</Name>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>2</Cost>
        <Spell>Loreanna</Spell>
        <Synergy>Trickster</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Loreanna</name> the character is able to channel the energy of others to transfer each to the other.
            The power of this skill is <check type="fai">Switch</check>. This skill fails if the distance between the targets in metres is greater than the power of this skill. This skill also fails if the target is unwilling and the difference between the targets' <HP/> is greater than the power of this skill. The targets are now each standing where the other was standing. Also their <HP/> has switched. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
            Note that this skill may raise a character's <HP/> above their <HPMax/>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>5</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Switch</skill></Power>
            <Quick>If X is greater than the HP difference and distance of two characters then they swap position and HP.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Taunt</Name>
        <Stat>Int</Stat>
        <Cost>3</Cost>
        <Synergy>Warrior</Synergy>
        <Text>
            This character has the ability to provoke their opponents into relentlessly attacking.
            The power of this skill is <check type="int">Taunt</check>. Any opposing character within a radius equal to the power of this skill in metres and <MP/> less than twice the power of this skill must attack this character in their next turn. Taunting requires a <name>Minor Action</name> but the character may use defence skills as normal this turn.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Minor</Action>
            <Mana>1</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Taunt</skill></Power>
            <Quick>All characters with at most 2X MP must attack the character.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Telekinesis</Name>
        <Stat>Int</Stat>
        <Cost>4</Cost>
        <Spell>Oxdoro</Spell>
        <Synergy>Mechanist</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Oxdoro</name> the caster can deftly manoeuvre small objects or crudely move large objects from a distance.
            If used to manipulate small objects this skill has power equal to its level without a check. Any object of weight less than the result weight can be telekinetically moved with precision. Delicate movement requries a <name>Major Action</name> but no <MP/>.
            If used to crudely move large objects the power of this skill is given by <check type="int">Telekinesis</check>. The mana cost is <MP>5</MP>. The distance that an object is moved is the result distance times the result weight divided by the object weight. For example: if a 60kg boulder is to be moved and the result of the check is 8 then the object can be moved 6 times 30 divided by 60 or 3 metres.
            If a creature is thrown in the above way into a wall or similar barrier then they are stunned for a number of turns equal to the extra distance they would have been thrown. For example a 80kg character is thrown with a Telekinesis check of power 12 and so would be thrown 4m. They hit a wall after 1m and so they are then stunned for 3 turns. Gross movement requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>2,1</Mana>
            <Power><skill>Telekinesis</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Precisely move objects of up to the result weight.</Quick>
        </Effect>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>6</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Telekinesis</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Move a large object a distance in metres equal to the result distance times result weight divided by object weight.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Track</Name>
        <Stat>Int</Stat>
        <Cost>2</Cost>
        <Synergy>Rogue</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By careful examination of the environment via visual and olfactory cues a character is able to track a creature path over any terrain.
            The power of the skill is <check type="int">Track</check>. The result level provides how deftly the character can follow the track. A Basic Pass albeit slowly. With a Pass the track can be followed at more or less walking pace. With a Prodigious Pass the track can be followed at a running pace. Tracking requires a <name>Major Action</name> for each turn spent tracking. If the character wishes to track using only a <name>Minor Action</name> they track with a result level one lower.
            Tracking becomes harder under certain circumstances. The tracking roll has the result reduced by 1 for each day that has passed since the trail was made. Soft ground imposes no penalty. However harder terrain will reduce the result level.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>3</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Track</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Track with power X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Unlock</Name>
        <Name>Lock</Name>
        <Invert/>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>3</Cost>
        <Spell>Ird'ken</Spell>
        <Synergy>Channeller</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Ird'ken</name> the caster is able to open any passage or bar any door.
            If used to unlock a divine or mechanical lock the power of this skill is given by <check type="fai">Unlock</check>. If the power of this skill is greater than the power of a lock then it is unlocked. Casting requires a <name>Minor Action</name>.
            If used to lock a barrier, such as a door or chest, the power of this skill is <check type="fai">Unlock</check>. Such a barrier becomes locked with a divine lock of power equal to the power of this skill. If the barrier already has a divine lock then the power of the divine lock becomes equal to the maximum of its current power and the power of this skill. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
            Locks can be both mechanical and divine. This skill attempts to unlock both with a single roll and can succeed to unlock one but fail to unlock the other.
            Multiple characters can pool their rolls when attempting either to lock or unlock a barrier.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>5</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Unlock</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Lock or unlock magically for strength X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Void</Name>
        <Require>Counter-spell</Require>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>3</Cost>
        <Spell>Ird'ken</Spell>
        <Synergy>Channeller</Synergy>
        <Text>
            By calling on the power of <name>Ird'ken</name> the power of any ongoing divine effect is sapped.
            The power of this skill is <check type="int">Void</check>. Any ongoing divine effect within a radius equal to the power of this skill in metres has its power reduced by the power of this skill to a minimum of zero. If the power of a divine skill reaches zero it is immediately cancelled and no ongoing effects or costs are applied. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
            This spell may be continued. If so then every spell either cast within the <name>Void</name> or targeted into the <name>Void</name> has its power reduced by the power of the original <name>Void</name> check. Ongoing costs are <MP>2</MP> and a <name>Minor Action</name>.
            This skill has no effect on a <name>Divine Contract</name> unless it specifically targets the contract in which case it does not have the above effect. The contract is immediately activated however it uses <check type="int">Void<times/>2</check> fewer dice. A character may not maliciously use this skill on a <name>Divine Contract</name> in an attempt to trigger this effect.
            Note that this effect applies to the effects of a spell and not casters. This means that the targets must be in the radius of this skill and not the casters. This skill can affect some characters but not others from a single spell and the caster of the original spell may choose to pay the ongoing cost for the remaining targets.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>8,2</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Void</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Cancel ongoing effects and new spells with power less than X.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Will of Arthur</Name>
        <Require>Follower of Arthur</Require>
        <Invert/>
        <Divide/>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>8</Cost>
        <Spell>Arthur</Spell>
        <Synergy>Battle Mage</Synergy>
        <Text>
            As a devout follower of <name>Arthur</name> the caster is able to draw extreme divine power from <name>Arthur</name>. They can increase the potency of all attack or defence abilities in their presence.
            The power of this skill is <check type="fai">Will of Arthur</check>. The duration of this skill is equal to the result duration. The caster chooses either attack or defence. For each nearby character the caster decides to increase or reduce the die type of attack or defense, as chosen earlier, of the character.
            If this skill is inverted then attack is swapped with defense and each character swaps whether it was increased or decreased. This skill is divisible. The caster may halve its power to increase the number of die types increased and reduced.
            This skill is unaffected by <name>Counter-spell</name>, <name>Spell Shield</name>, <name>Inversion</name>, <name>Steal Spell</name> and <name>Void</name>. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>15</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Will of Arthur</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Add or remove X to all attack skills, defence skills or both.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Will of Innodi</Name>
        <Require>Follower of Innodi</Require>
        <Invert/>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>8</Cost>
        <Spell>Innodi</Spell>
        <Synergy>Necromancer</Synergy>
        <Text>
            As a devout follower of <name>Innodi</name> the caster is able to draw extreme divine power from <name>Innodi</name>. They can channel life force in or out of the surrounding environment healing or grievously harming those around them.
            The power of this skill is <check type="fai">Will of Innodi</check>. For each nearby character the caster chooses that that character either heals or sustains a number of <name>Deep Wounds</name> equal to the result level of this skilll.
            This skill is unaffected by <name>Counter-spell</name>, <name>Spell Shield</name>, <name>Inversion</name>, <name>Steal Spell</name> and <name>Void</name>. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>15</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Will of Innodi</skill></Power>
            <Quick>All characters gain or lose X deep wounds.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Will of Ird'ken</Name>
        <Require>Follower of Ird'ken</Require>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>8</Cost>
        <Spell>Ird'ken</Spell>
        <Synergy>Channeller</Synergy>
        <Text>
            As a devout follower of <name>Ird'ken</name> the caster is able to draw extreme divine power from <name>Ird'ken</name> to cause chaos or order.
            The power of this skill is <check type-="fai">Follower of Ird'ken</check>. The duration of this skill is the result duration. Whenever each nearby character in the effect performs a <name>Major Action</name> they instead pick the result level number of skills. The caster then chooses which skill the target actually performs. The target still chooses the specifics of the skill they use such as targets. If the target does not have sufficient skills that have <name>Major Action</name>s then they pick as many skills as they can.
            This skill is unaffected by <name>Counter-spell</name>, <name>Spell Shield</name>, <name>Inversion</name>, <name>Steal Spell</name> and <name>Void</name>. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>15</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Will of Ird'ken</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Choose targets' Major Actions from a list numbering result level skills.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Will of Loreanna</Name>
        <Require>Follower of Loreanna</Require>
        <Divide/>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>8</Cost>
        <Spell>Loreanna</Spell>
        <Synergy>Trickster</Synergy>
        <Text>
            As a devout follower of <name>Loreanna</name> the caster is able to draw extreme divine power from <name>Loreanna</name>. Loreanna imparts skill and knowledge to an individual.
            The power of this skill is <check type="fai">Will of Loreanna</check>. The duration of this skill is the power duration. The target gains one result level to any ability used or the skills <name>Locks and Traps</name>, <name>Lore</name>, <name>Observation</name>, <name>Sense</name> and <name>Stealth</name>. If the target is untrained in the ability they also reduce the untrained penalty by one level. This effect is <name>Divisible</name> and so by reducing the duration the caster can increase the number of targets.
            This skill is unaffected by <name>Counter-spell</name>, <name>Spell Shield</name>, <name>Inversion</name>, <name>Steal Spell</name> and <name>Void</name>. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>15</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Will of Loreanna</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Target gains +1 to abilties and reduces untrained penalties. Divide to increase number of targets.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Will of Oxdoro</Name>
        <Require>Follower of Oxdoro</Require>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>8</Cost>
        <Spell>Oxdoro</Spell>
        <Synergy>Mechanist</Synergy>
        <Text>
            As a devout follower of <name>Oxdoro</name> the caster is able to draw extreme divine power from <name>Oxdoro</name>. They can stop time for everyone except themselves bringing objects and creatures back to life by their touch.
            The power of this skill is <check type="fai">Will of Oxdoro</check>. Time is frozen for the result duration of the check. Any character may make a <check type="fai">Will of Oxdoro</check> to see if they are frozen. The caster and any character with a check at least the power of this skill is not frozen. Any character or object touched by a character not frozen is no longer frozen. A character may use a <name>Minor Action</name> to touch another character or object or a <name>Major Action</name> to touch up to two characters or objects. A frozen character does not get a chance to defend when frozen. However this counts as touching the defending character and so they are no longer frozen.
            This skill is unaffected by <name>Counter-spell</name>, <name>Spell Shield</name>, <name>Inversion</name>, <name>Steal Spell</name> and <name>Void</name>. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>15</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Will of Oxdoro</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Freeze everything but characters with the Will of Oxdoro. Anything they touch unfreezes.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>
    
    <Skill>
        <Name>Will of Travaer</Name>
        <Require>Follower of Travaer</Require>
        <Stat>Fai</Stat>
        <Cost>8</Cost>
        <Spell>Travaer</Spell>
        <Synergy>Lore</Synergy>
        <Text>
            As a devout follower of <name>Travaer</name> the caster is able to draw extreme divine power from <name>Travaer</name>. The caster can invert any spell or skill used in their presence.
            The power of this skill is <name>Will of Travaer</name>. The duration of this skill is equal to its result duration. Any invertible spell that is cast nearby is affected by this skill. The caster of this skill may invert the spell at their discretion. If the invertible spell has multiple targets then the effect is inverted for all targets.
            This only affects newly cast spells and does not affect ongoing effects. This can affect the will of other deities.
            This skill is unaffected by <name>Counter-spell</name>, <name>Spell Shield</name>, <name>Inversion</name>, <name>Steal Spell</name> and <name>Void</name>. Casting requires a <name>Major Action</name>. While this skill does not have a divine token, it is a spell.
        </Text>
        <Effect>
            <Action>Major</Action>
            <Mana>15</Mana>
            <Power type="roll"><skill>Will of Travaer</skill></Power>
            <Quick>Caster gets the chance to invert any invertible spell.</Quick>
        </Effect>
    </Skill>

</Skills>